<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pierre Zemb</title>
    <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Pierre Zemb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 19:11:11 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscover the known data universe with NASA dataset</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/nasa-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 19:11:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/nasa-datasets/</guid>
      <description>Abstract For many years humanity has been exploring the skies, dreaming of interstellar voyages and new planetary colonies. And you, do you want to go 3h with us to discover the universe?
It turns out that NASA has a great public dataset, especially one that is used to search for exoplanets, that is, planets outside our solar system.
During this Hands-on, we will guide you through the different stages of rediscovering exoplanets using Warp10, an open-source time series processing platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 18:34:45 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/about/</guid>
      <description>$ whoami I&amp;rsquo;m an Infrastructure Engineer at OVH.
I have a passion for distributed systems, specifically when it comes with scalability and performance issues.
I&amp;rsquo;m the deep-dive&amp;rsquo;s type of guy, i.e. I&amp;rsquo;m not scared of having to optimize components like the JVM or the Linux Kernel to reach my goal, or read Hbase basecode to understand how it internally works.
I&amp;rsquo;m developing software using Go, Rust and Java, as well as performing on-call duty on more than 500 servers, including several Hadoop clusters.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrics Experience beyond protocols</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/metrics-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 15:38:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/metrics-experience/</guid>
      <description> Occurences  Paris Open Source Summit, 2017  Ressources The slides are available here.
Photos and Tweets Let&amp;#39;s discover @OvhMetrics experience with @PierreZ at #OSSPARIS17 pic.twitter.com/Xz1tRTNcFW
&amp;mdash; Collignon Rémi (@miton1810) December 7, 2017  </description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing HelloExoWorld: The quest to discover exoplanets with Warp10 and Tensorflow</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/introducing-helloexoworld-the-quest-to-discover-exoplanets-with-warp10-and-tensorflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 10:23:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/introducing-helloexoworld-the-quest-to-discover-exoplanets-with-warp10-and-tensorflow/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
Artist’s impression of the super-Earth exoplanet LHS 1140b By ESO/spaceengine.org — CC BY 4.0
My passion for programming was kind of late, I typed my first line of code at my engineering school. It then became a passion, something I’m willing to do at work, on my free-time, at night or the week-end.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Engage maximum warp speed in time series analysis with WarpScript</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/engage-maximum-warp-speed-in-time-series-analysis-with-warpscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 20:43:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/engage-maximum-warp-speed-in-time-series-analysis-with-warpscript/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
We, at Metrics Data Platform, are working everyday with Warp10 Platform, an open source Time Series database. You may not know it because it’s not as famous as Prometheus or InfluxDB but Warp10 is the most powerful and generic solution to store and analyze sensor data. It’s the core of Metrics, and many internal teams from OVH are using Metrics Data Platform to monitor their infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Event-driven architecture 101</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/eventdriven-architecture-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 17:19:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/eventdriven-architecture-101/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
Do your own cover on http://dev.to/rly
I’m still a student, so my point of view could be far from reality, be gentle ;)
tl;dr: Queue messaging are cool. Use them at the core of your architecture.I’m currently playing a lot around Kafka and Flink at work. I also discovered Vert.x at my local JUG.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Let’s talk about containers</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/lets-talk-about-containers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 18:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/lets-talk-about-containers/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
English is not my first language, so the whole story may have some mistakes… corrections and fixes will be greatly appreciated. I’m also still a student, so my point of view could be far from “production ready”, be gentle ;-)
In the last two years, there’s been a technology that became really hype.</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>