<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>foundationdb on Pierre Zemb</title>
    <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/foundationdb/</link>
    <description>Recent content in foundationdb on Pierre Zemb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34;&gt;Some Rights Reserved&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 10:24:27 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/foundationdb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Announcing Record-Store, a new (experimental) place for your data</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/announcing-record-store/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 10:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/announcing-record-store/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: I&amp;rsquo;m really happy to announce my latest open-source project called Record-Store 🚀 Please check it out on https://pierrez.github.io/record-store.
What? Record-Store is a layer running on top of FoundationDB. It provides abstractions to create, load and deletes customer-defined data called records, which are hold into a RecordSpace. We would like to have this kind of flow for developers:
 Opening KeySpace, for example prod/users Create a protobuf definition which will be used as schema Upsert schema Push records Query records delete records  You need another KeySpace to store another type of data, or maybe a KeySpace dedicated to production env?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🇫🇷 BigData Hebdo 93 : FoundationDB</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/podcasts/bdh-93/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 01:22:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/podcasts/bdh-93/</guid>
      <description> </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes about FoundationDB</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 10:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</guid>
      <description>Notes About is a blogpost serie you will find a lot of links, videos, quotes, podcasts to click on about a specific topic. Today we will discover FoundationDB.
 Overview of FoundationDB As stated in the official documentation:
 FoundationDB is a distributed database designed to handle large volumes of structured data across clusters of commodity servers. It organizes data as an ordered key-value store and employs ACID transactions for all operations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
