<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Pierre Zemb&#x27;s Blog - foundationdb</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr</link>
      <description>Pierre Zemb personal blog</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/foundationdb/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Designing Rust FDB Workloads That Actually Find Bugs</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/writing-rust-fdb-workloads-that-find-bugs/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/writing-rust-fdb-workloads-that-find-bugs/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/writing-rust-fdb-workloads-that-find-bugs/">&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;diving-into-foundationdb-simulation&#x2F;&quot;&gt;one trillion CPU-hours of simulation testing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, FoundationDB has been stress-tested under conditions far worse than any production environment. Network partitions, disk failures, Byzantine faults. FDB handles them all. &lt;strong&gt;But what about your code?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Your layer sits on top of FDB. Your indexes, your transaction logic, your retry handling. How do you know it survives chaos?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Clever Cloud, we were building &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;materia&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Materia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, our serverless database product. We were afraid to ship our layer code without the same level of testing FDB itself enjoys. So we hacked our way into FDB&#x27;s simulation framework using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;tree&#x2F;4ed057a&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&quot;&gt;foundationdb-simulation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. On our first seed, simulation surfaced one of the most dreaded edge cases for FDB layer developers: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;developer-guide.html#transactions-with-unknown-results&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The client can&#x27;t always know if a transaction committed before the connection dropped. Our atomic counter increments were sometimes running twice. In production, you might see this once every few months under heavy load and during failures. In simulation? &lt;strong&gt;Almost immediately.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post won&#x27;t walk you through the code mechanics. The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;crates.io&#x2F;crates&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&quot;&gt;foundationdb-simulation crate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and its &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;tree&#x2F;4ed057a&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&quot;&gt;README&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; cover that. Instead, this teaches you how to &lt;strong&gt;design&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; workloads that catch real bugs. Whether you&#x27;re a junior engineer or an LLM helping write tests, these principles will guide you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-autonomous-testing-works&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why-autonomous-testing-works&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why-autonomous-testing-works&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Why Autonomous Testing Works&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional testing has you write specific tests for scenarios you imagined. But as Will Wilson put it at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=eZ1mmqlq-mY&quot;&gt;Bug Bash 2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;&quot;The most dangerous bugs occur in states you never imagined possible.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The key insight of autonomous testing (what FDB&#x27;s simulation embodies) is that instead of writing tests, you write a &lt;strong&gt;test generator&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you ran it for infinite time, it would eventually produce all possible tests you could have written. You don&#x27;t have infinite time, so instead you get a probability distribution over all possible tests. And probability distributions are leaky: they cover cases you never would have thought to test.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why simulation finds bugs so fast. You&#x27;re not testing what you thought to test. You&#x27;re testing what the probability distribution happens to generate, which includes edge cases you&#x27;d never have written explicitly. Add fault injection (a probability distribution over all possible ways the world can conspire to screw you) and now you&#x27;re finding bugs that would take months or years to surface in production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what got me interested in simulation in the first place: how do you test the things you see during on-call shifts? Those weird transient bugs at 3 AM, the race conditions that happen once a month, the edge cases you only discover when production is on fire. Simulation shifts that complexity from SRE time to SWE time. What was a 3 AM page becomes a daytime debugging session. What&#x27;s a high-pressure incident becomes a reproducible test case you can bisect, rewind, and experiment with freely.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sequential-luck-problem&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-sequential-luck-problem&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-sequential-luck-problem&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Sequential Luck Problem&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s why rare bugs are so hard to find: imagine a bug that requires three unlikely events in sequence. Each event has a 1&#x2F;1000 probability. Finding that bug requires 1&#x2F;1,000,000,000 attempts, roughly a billion tries with random testing. &lt;strong&gt;But here&#x27;s the good news for Rust workloads&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: you don&#x27;t solve this problem yourself. FDB&#x27;s simulation handles fault injection. BUGGIFY injects failures at arbitrary code points. Network partitions appear and disappear. Disks fail. Machines crash and restart. The simulator explores failure combinations that would take years to encounter in production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your job is different. You need to design operations that exercise interesting code paths. Not just reads and writes, but the edge cases your users will inevitably trigger. And you need to write invariants that CATCH bugs when simulation surfaces them. After a million injected faults, how do you prove your data is still correct? This division of labor is the key insight: FDB injects chaos, you verify correctness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-your-operation-alphabet&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#designing-your-operation-alphabet&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: designing-your-operation-alphabet&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Designing Your Operation Alphabet&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;operation alphabet&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is the complete set of operations your workload can perform. This is where most workloads fail: they test happy paths with uniform distribution and miss the edge cases that break production. Think about three categories:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Normal operations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; with realistic weights. In production, maybe 80% of your traffic is reads, 15% is simple writes, 5% is complex updates. Your workload should reflect this, because bugs often hide in the interactions between operation types. A workload that runs 50% reads and 50% writes tests different code paths than one that runs 95% reads and 5% writes. Both might be valid, but they&#x27;ll find different bugs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adversarial inputs&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; that customers will inevitably send. Empty strings. Maximum-length values. Null bytes in the middle of strings. Unicode edge cases. Boundary integers (0, -1, MAX_INT). Customers never respect your API specs, so model the chaos they create.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nemesis operations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; that break things on purpose. Delete random data mid-test. Clear ranges that &quot;shouldn&#x27;t&quot; be cleared. Crash batch jobs mid-execution to test recovery. Run compaction every operation instead of daily. Create conflict storms where multiple clients hammer the same key. Approach the 10MB transaction limit. These operations stress your error handling and recovery paths. The rare operations are where bugs hide. That batch job running once a day in production? In simulation, you&#x27;ll hit its partial-failure edge case in minutes, but only if your operation alphabet includes it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-invariants&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#designing-invariants&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: designing-invariants&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Designing Invariants&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After simulation runs thousands of operations with injected faults, network partitions, and machine crashes, how do you know your data is still correct? Unlike FDB&#x27;s internal testing, Rust workloads can&#x27;t inject assertions at arbitrary code points. You verify correctness in the &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; phase, after the chaos ends. The key question: &lt;strong&gt;&quot;After all this, how do I PROVE my data is still correct?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One critical tip: validate during &lt;code&gt;start()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, not just in &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Don&#x27;t wait until the end to discover corruption. After each operation (or batch of operations), read back the data and verify it matches expectations. If you&#x27;re maintaining a counter, read it and check the bounds. If you&#x27;re building an index, query it immediately after insertion. Early validation catches bugs closer to their source, making debugging far easier. The &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; phase is your final safety net, but continuous validation during execution is where you&#x27;ll catch most issues.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four patterns dominate invariant design:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference Models&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; maintain an in-memory copy of expected state. Every operation updates both the database and the reference model. In &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, you compare them. If they diverge, something went wrong. Use &lt;code&gt;BTreeMap&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (not &lt;code&gt;HashMap&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) for deterministic iteration. This pattern works best for single-client workloads where you can track state locally.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conservation Laws&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; track quantities that must stay constant. Inventory transfers between warehouses shouldn&#x27;t change total inventory. Money transfers between accounts shouldn&#x27;t create or destroy money. Sum everything up and verify the conservation law holds. This pattern is elegant because it doesn&#x27;t require tracking individual operations, just the aggregate property.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structural Integrity&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; verifies data structures remain valid. If you maintain a secondary index, verify every index entry points to an existing record and every record appears in the index exactly once. If you maintain a linked list in FDB, traverse it and confirm every node is reachable. The cycle validation pattern (creating a circular list where nodes point to each other) is a classic technique from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;231f762&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;Cycle.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;FDB&#x27;s own Cycle workload&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. After chaos, traverse the cycle and verify you visit exactly N nodes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operation Logging&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; solves two problems at once: &lt;code&gt;maybe_committed&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; uncertainty and multi-client coordination. The trick from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;231f762&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;AtomicOps.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;FDB&#x27;s own AtomicOps workload&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;log the intent alongside the operation in the same transaction&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Write both your operation AND a log entry recording what you intended. Since they&#x27;re in the same transaction, they either both commit or neither does. No uncertainty. For multi-client workloads, each client logs under its own prefix (e.g., &lt;code&gt;log&#x2F;{client_id}&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). In &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, client 0 reads all logs from all clients, replays them to compute expected state, and compares against actual state. If they diverge, something went wrong, and you&#x27;ll know exactly which operations succeeded. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;4ed057a&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&#x2F;examples&#x2F;atomic&#x2F;lib.rs&quot;&gt;Rust atomic workload example&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for a complete implementation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-determinism-rules&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-determinism-rules&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-determinism-rules&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Determinism Rules&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FDB&#x27;s simulation is deterministic. Same seed, same execution path, same bugs. This is the superpower that lets you reproduce failures. But determinism is fragile. Break it, and you lose reproducibility. Five rules to remember:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BTreeMap, not HashMap&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: HashMap iteration order is non-deterministic&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;context.rnd(), not rand::random()&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: All randomness must come from the seeded PRNG&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;context.now(), not SystemTime::now()&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Use simulation time, not wall clock&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;db.run(), not manual retry loops&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: The framework handles retries and &lt;code&gt;maybe_committed&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; correctly&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No tokio::spawn()&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: The simulation runs on a custom executor, spawning breaks it&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take nothing else from this post, memorize these. Break any of them and your failures become unreproducible. You&#x27;ll see a bug once and never find it again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;architecture-the-three-crate-pattern&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#architecture-the-three-crate-pattern&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: architecture-the-three-crate-pattern&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Architecture: The Three-Crate Pattern&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real production systems use tokio, gRPC, REST frameworks, all of which break simulation determinism. You can&#x27;t just drop your production binary into the simulator. The solution is separating your FDB operations into a simulation-friendly crate:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;my-project&#x2F;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;├── my-fdb-service&#x2F;      # Core FDB operations - NO tokio
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;├── my-grpc-server&#x2F;      # Production layer (tokio + tonic)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;└── my-fdb-workloads&#x2F;    # Simulation tests
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service crate contains pure FDB transaction logic with no async runtime dependency. The server crate wraps it for production. The workloads crate tests the actual service logic under simulation chaos. This lets you test your real production code, not a reimplementation that might have different bugs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-pitfalls&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#common-pitfalls&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: common-pitfalls&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Common Pitfalls&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the determinism rules above, these mistakes will bite you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running setup or check on all clients.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The framework runs multiple clients concurrently. If every client initializes data in &lt;code&gt;setup()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, you get duplicate initialization. If every client validates in &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, you get inconsistent results. Use &lt;code&gt;if self.client_id == 0&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to ensure only one client handles initialization and validation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forgetting maybe_committed.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The &lt;code&gt;db.run()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; closure receives a &lt;code&gt;maybe_committed&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; flag indicating the previous attempt might have succeeded. If you&#x27;re doing non-idempotent operations like atomic increments, you need either truly idempotent transactions or &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;automatic-txn-fdb-730&#x2F;&quot;&gt;automatic idempotency&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in FDB 7.3+. Ignoring this flag means your workload might count operations twice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storing SimDatabase between phases.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Each phase (&lt;code&gt;setup&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;start&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;check&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) gets a fresh database reference. Storing the old one leads to undefined behavior. Always use the &lt;code&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; parameter passed to each method.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wrapping FdbError in custom error types.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The &lt;code&gt;db.run()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; retry mechanism checks if errors are retryable via &lt;code&gt;FdbError::is_retryable()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. If you wrap &lt;code&gt;FdbError&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; in your own error type (like &lt;code&gt;anyhow::Error&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or a custom enum), the retry logic can&#x27;t see the underlying error and won&#x27;t retry. Keep &lt;code&gt;FdbError&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; unwrapped in your transaction closures, or ensure your error type preserves retryability information.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assuming setup is safe from failures.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; BUGGIFY is disabled during &lt;code&gt;setup()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, so you might think transactions can&#x27;t fail. But simulation randomizes FDB knobs, which can still cause transaction failures. Always use &lt;code&gt;db.run()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; with retry logic even in setup, or wrap your setup in a retry loop.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-value&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-real-value&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-real-value&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Real Value&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That &lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; edge case appeared on our first simulation seed. In production, we&#x27;d still be hunting it months later. But the real value of simulation testing isn&#x27;t just finding bugs, it&#x27;s &lt;strong&gt;forcing you to think about correctness.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; When you design a workload, you&#x27;re forced to ask: &quot;What happens when this retries during a partition?&quot; &quot;How do I verify correctness when transactions can commit in any order?&quot; &quot;What invariants must hold no matter what chaos occurs?&quot; Designing for chaos becomes natural. And if it survives simulation, it survives production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out with questions or to share your simulation workloads. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">rust</category>
          <category domain="tag">testing</category>
          <category domain="tag">simulation</category>
          <category domain="tag">deterministic</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed-systems</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Diving into FoundationDB&#x27;s Simulation Framework</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/diving-into-foundationdb-simulation/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/diving-into-foundationdb-simulation/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/diving-into-foundationdb-simulation/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;tags&#x2F;diving-into&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Diving Into&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a blogpost series where we are digging a specific part of the project&#x27;s codebase. In this episode, we will dig into the implementation behind FoundationDB&#x27;s simulation framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After years of on-call shifts running FoundationDB at Clever Cloud, here&#x27;s what I&#x27;ve learned: &lt;strong&gt;I&#x27;ve never been woken up by FDB&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Every production incident traced back to our code, our infrastructure, our mistakes. Never FDB itself. That kind of reliability doesn&#x27;t happen by accident.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret? &lt;strong&gt;Deterministic simulation testing&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. FoundationDB runs the real database software (not mocks, not stubs) in a discrete-event simulator alongside randomized workloads and aggressive fault injection. All sources of nondeterminism are abstracted: network, disk, time, and random number generation. Multiple FDB servers communicate through a simulated network in a single-threaded process. The simulator injects machine crashes, rack failures, network partitions, disk corruption, bit flips. Every failure mode you can imagine, happening in rapid succession, deterministically. Same seed, same execution path, same bugs, every single time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After roughly &lt;strong&gt;one trillion CPU-hours of simulation testing&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, FoundationDB has been stress-tested under conditions far worse than any production environment will ever encounter. The development environment is deliberately harsher than production: network partitions every few seconds, machine crashes mid-transaction, disks randomly swapped between nodes on reboot. If your code survives the simulator, production is easy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve written before about &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;simulation-driven-development&#x2F;&quot;&gt;simulation-driven development&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;testing-prevention-vs-discovery&#x2F;&quot;&gt;testing prevention vs discovery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Those posts cover the concepts and benefits. This post is different: &lt;strong&gt;this is how FoundationDB actually implements deterministic simulation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Interface swapping, deterministic event loops, BUGGIFY chaos injection, Flow actors, and the architecture that makes it all work. We&#x27;re going deep into the implementation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;fdb-simulation-deep-dive&#x2F;simulator-architecture.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;FoundationDB Simulator Architecture&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;FoundationDB&#x27;s simulation architecture: the same FDB server code runs in both the simulator process (using simulated I&#x2F;O) and the real world (using real I&#x2F;O)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-trick-interface-swapping&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-trick-interface-swapping&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-trick-interface-swapping&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Trick: Interface Swapping&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genius of FDB&#x27;s simulation is surprisingly simple: &lt;strong&gt;the same code runs in both production and simulation by swapping interface implementations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The global &lt;code&gt;g_network&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; pointer holds an &lt;code&gt;INetwork&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; interface. In production, this points to &lt;code&gt;Net2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which creates real TCP connections using Boost.ASIO. In simulation, it points to &lt;code&gt;Sim2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbrpc&#x2F;sim2.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;sim2.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), which creates &lt;code&gt;Sim2Conn&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; objects (fake connections that write to in-memory buffers).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When code needs to send data, it gets a &lt;code&gt;Reference&amp;lt;IConnection&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; from the network layer. In production, that&#x27;s a real socket. In simulation, it&#x27;s &lt;code&gt;Sim2Conn&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbrpc&#x2F;sim2.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;sim2.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) with a &lt;code&gt;std::deque&amp;lt;uint8_t&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; buffer. Network latency? The simulator adds &lt;code&gt;delay()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; calls with values from &lt;code&gt;deterministicRandom()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Packet loss? Just throw &lt;code&gt;connection_failed()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Network partition? &lt;code&gt;Sim2Conn&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; checks &lt;code&gt;g_clogging.disconnected()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and refuses delivery. &lt;strong&gt;It&#x27;s all just memory operations with delays&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, running single-threaded and completely deterministic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this truly deterministic is &lt;code&gt;deterministicRandom()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, a seeded PRNG that replaces all randomness. Every network latency value, every backoff delay (like the &lt;code&gt;Peer&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&#x27;s exponential reconnection timing), every process crash timing goes through the same deterministic stream. Same seed, same execution path, every single time. When a test fails after 1 trillion simulated operations, you can reproduce the exact failure by running with the same seed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;biasing-the-simulator-buggify&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#biasing-the-simulator-buggify&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: biasing-the-simulator-buggify&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Biasing the Simulator: BUGGIFY&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most deep bugs need a rare combination of events. A network partition &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; a slow disk &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; a coordinator crash happening at the exact same moment. The probability of all three aligning randomly? Astronomical. You&#x27;d burn CPU-centuries waiting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB solves this with &lt;code&gt;BUGGIFY&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, spread throughout the codebase. Each &lt;code&gt;BUGGIFY&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; point fires 25% of the time, deterministically, so every test explores a different corner of the state space (Alex Miller&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;transactional.blog&#x2F;simulation&#x2F;buggify&quot;&gt;excellent post on BUGGIFY&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; covers the implementation details).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s take timeout handling in data distribution as an example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; DDShardTracker.actor.cpp (fdbserver&#x2F;DDShardTracker.actor.cpp:1508)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;choose {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;when&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;wait&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(g_network-&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;isSimulated&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() &amp;amp;&amp;amp; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;BUGGIFY_WITH_PROB&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.01&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) ? &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Never&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                                          : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;fetchTopKShardMetrics_impl&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(self, req))) {}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;when&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;wait&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;delay&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(SERVER_KNOBS-&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;DD_SHARD_METRICS_TIMEOUT&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))) {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Timeout path
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Never()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; future never completes. Literally hangs forever. This happens only in simulation (&lt;code&gt;g_network-&amp;gt;isSimulated()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) and with 1% probability (&lt;code&gt;BUGGIFY_WITH_PROB(0.01)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). When it fires, the operation gets stuck, forcing the timeout branch to execute. Simple, elegant failure injection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&#x27;s the trick: &lt;strong&gt;the timeout value itself is also buggified&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; ServerKnobs.cpp
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( DD_SHARD_METRICS_TIMEOUT, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;60.0 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Production: 60 seconds
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( randomize &amp;amp;&amp;amp; BUGGIFY ) DD_SHARD_METRICS_TIMEOUT = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Simulation: 0.1 seconds!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Production timeout: 60 seconds. BUGGIFY timeout: 0.1 seconds (600x shorter). The shrinking timeout window means legitimate operations are far more likely to hit timeout paths. Even without &lt;code&gt;Never()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; forcing a hang, simulated network delays and slow operations will trigger timeouts constantly. When &lt;code&gt;Never()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; does fire, you get guaranteed timeout execution. Every knob marked &lt;code&gt;if (randomize &amp;amp;&amp;amp; BUGGIFY)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; becomes a chaos variable. Timeouts shrink, cache sizes drop, I&#x2F;O patterns randomize.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates &lt;strong&gt;combinatorial explosion&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. FoundationDB has hundreds of randomized knobs. Each BUGGIFY-enabled test run picks a different configuration: maybe connection monitors are 4x slower, but file I&#x2F;O is using 32KB blocks, and cache size is 1000 entries, and reconnection delays are doubled. The next run? Completely different knob values. Same code, thousands of different operating environments. After one trillion simulated operations across countless test runs, you&#x27;ve stress-tested your code under scenarios that would take decades to encounter in production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-developer-workflow-simulation-as-ci-cd&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-developer-workflow-simulation-as-ci-cd&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-developer-workflow-simulation-as-ci-cd&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Developer Workflow: Simulation as CI&#x2F;CD&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the FoundationDB developer experience: &lt;strong&gt;write code, run a few local simulation tests to catch obvious bugs, submit your merge request, then let the machines do the hard work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every pull request triggers &lt;strong&gt;hundreds of thousands of simulation tests&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; running on hundreds of cores for hours before a human even begins code review. Different seeds explore different execution paths, different failure timings, different BUGGIFY configurations. Nightly testing runs tens of thousands more simulations, crawling through edge cases you&#x27;d never think to test manually.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days when FoundationDB was still a company, they took this philosophy to its logical extreme: &lt;strong&gt;merge requests were automatically merged if simulation passed&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. No human approval needed. The simulation was so trusted that passing tests meant the code was production-ready. (You can hear more about FoundationDB&#x27;s early development culture on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=C1nZzQqcPZw&amp;amp;list=PLh4UhOpNuTJO1S8xkfa3QmQzJemsUhuL8&amp;amp;index=6&quot;&gt;The BugBash Podcast&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changes how you think about distributed systems development. Instead of spending hours debugging race conditions or trying to mentally model all possible failure scenarios, you focus on building features. The simulation finds the edge cases. It discovers the bugs you&#x27;d never anticipate. It stress-tests your code under conditions that would take years to encounter in production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scale ramps up through the development cycle: thousands of seeds during merge request testing, tens of thousands in nightly runs, potentially millions during major release cycles. Each seed represents a completely different execution path through your code. By the time your change reaches production, it&#x27;s survived more chaos than most distributed systems see in their entire lifetime.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The confidence this gives developers is extraordinary&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: if your code survives hundreds of thousands of simulated disasters, production feels easy in comparison.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;flow-actors-and-cooperative-multitasking&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#flow-actors-and-cooperative-multitasking&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: flow-actors-and-cooperative-multitasking&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Flow: Actors and Cooperative Multitasking&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB doesn&#x27;t use traditional threads. It uses Flow, a custom actor model built on C++. Here&#x27;s a simple example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;ACTOR Future&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;int&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;asyncAdd&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(Future&amp;lt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;int&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;int &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;offset&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;int&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; value = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;wait&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(f);  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Suspend until f completes, then resume with its value
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;return&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; value + offset;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ACTOR&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; keyword marks functions that can use &lt;code&gt;wait()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. When you call &lt;code&gt;wait(f)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, the actor &lt;strong&gt;suspends&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. It returns control to the event loop and resumes later when the &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; completes, continuing with the result. No blocking. All asynchronous. Use the &lt;code&gt;state&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; keyword for variables that need to persist across multiple &lt;code&gt;wait()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; calls.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know Rust&#x27;s async&#x2F;await, Flow is the same concept. &lt;code&gt;ACTOR&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; functions are like &lt;code&gt;async fn&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;wait()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is like &lt;code&gt;.await&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Future&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is like Rust&#x27;s &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. The difference? Flow was built in 2009 for C++, and gets compiled by &lt;code&gt;actorcompiler.h&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; into state machines rather than relying on language support.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same Flow code runs in both production and simulation. An actor waiting for network I&#x2F;O gets a real socket in production, a simulated buffer in simulation. The code doesn&#x27;t know the difference. The Flow documentation at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;flow.html&quot;&gt;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;flow.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; covers the full programming model.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;single-threaded-time-travel-the-event-loop&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#single-threaded-time-travel-the-event-loop&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: single-threaded-time-travel-the-event-loop&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Single-Threaded Time Travel: The Event Loop&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of actors running concurrently. Coordinators electing leaders, transaction logs replicating commits, storage servers handling reads. All happening in &lt;strong&gt;one thread&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick is cooperative multitasking. Actors yield control with &lt;code&gt;wait()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. When all actors are waiting, the event loop can &lt;strong&gt;advance simulated time&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;pre class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
        flowchart TD
    Start([Event Loop]) --&amp;gt; CheckReady{Any actors&amp;lt;br&amp;#x2F;&amp;gt;ready to run?}
    CheckReady --&amp;gt;|Yes| RunActor[Run next ready actor&amp;lt;br&amp;#x2F;&amp;gt;until it hits wait]
    RunActor --&amp;gt; CheckReady
    CheckReady --&amp;gt;|No, all waiting| CheckPending{Any pending&amp;lt;br&amp;#x2F;&amp;gt;futures?}
    CheckPending --&amp;gt;|Yes| AdvanceTime[Advance simulated clock&amp;lt;br&amp;#x2F;&amp;gt;to next event]
    AdvanceTime --&amp;gt; CheckReady
    CheckPending --&amp;gt;|No| Done([Simulation complete])
    &lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the key insight: when all actors are blocked waiting on futures, the event loop finds the next scheduled event (the earliest timestamp) and &lt;strong&gt;jumps the simulated clock forward&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to that time. Then it wakes the actors waiting for that event and runs them until they &lt;code&gt;wait()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example: 100 storage servers each execute &lt;code&gt;wait(delay(deterministicRandom()-&amp;gt;random01() * 60.0))&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. In wall-clock time, this takes microseconds. In simulated time, these delays are spread across 60 seconds. The event loop processes them in order, advancing time as it goes. &lt;strong&gt;Zero wall-clock time has passed. 60 simulated seconds have passed.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives you:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compressed time&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Years of uptime in seconds of testing. &lt;code&gt;wait(delay(86400.0))&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; simulates 24 hours instantly.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perfect determinism&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Single-threaded execution means no race conditions. Same seed, same event ordering, exact same execution path.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducibility&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Test fails after 1 trillion simulated operations? Run again with the same seed, get the exact same failure at the exact same point.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No actor ever blocks. They all cooperate, yielding control back to the event loop. This is the foundation that makes realistic cluster simulation possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-simulated-cluster&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#building-the-simulated-cluster&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: building-the-simulated-cluster&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Building the Simulated Cluster&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we understand Flow actors and the event loop, let&#x27;s see what runs on it. SimulatedCluster &lt;strong&gt;builds an entire distributed cluster in memory&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;SimulatedCluster&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; starts by generating a random cluster configuration: 1-5 datacenters, 1-10+ machines per DC, different storage engines (memory, ssd, redwood-1), different replication modes (single, double, triple). Every test run gets a different topology.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actor hierarchy looks like this: SimulatedCluster creates machine actors (&lt;code&gt;simulatedMachine&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). Each machine actor creates process actors (&lt;code&gt;simulatedFDBDRebooter&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). Each process actor runs &lt;strong&gt;actual fdbserver code&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The machine actor sits in an infinite loop: wait for all processes to die, delay 10 simulated seconds, reboot.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The same fdbserver code that runs in production runs here&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. No mocks. No stubs. Real transaction logs writing to simulated disk. Real storage engines (RocksDB, Redwood). Real Paxos consensus. The only difference? &lt;code&gt;Sim2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; network instead of &lt;code&gt;Net2&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, BUGGIFY shows up here too. Remember how BUGGIFY shrinks timeouts and injects failures? It also does something &lt;strong&gt;completely insane&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; during machine reboots. When a machine reboots, the simulator can &lt;strong&gt;swap its disks&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; SimulatedCluster.actor.cpp - machine reboot
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;state &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;bool&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; swap = killType == ISimulator::KillType::Reboot &amp;amp;&amp;amp;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;BUGGIFY_WITH_PROB&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.75&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) &amp;amp;&amp;amp;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                  g_simulator-&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;canSwapToMachine&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(localities.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;zoneId&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;());
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(swap) {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    availableFolders[localities.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;dcId&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()].&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;push_back&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(myFolders);  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Return my disks to pool
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    myFolders = availableFolders[localities.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;dcId&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()][randomIndex];  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Get random disks from pool
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;75% of the time when BUGGIFY is enabled, a rebooting machine gets &lt;strong&gt;random disks from the datacenter pool&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Maybe it gets its own disks back. Maybe it gets another machine&#x27;s disks with completely different data. Maybe it gets the disks from a machine that was destroyed 10 minutes ago. Your storage server just woke up with someone else&#x27;s data (or no data at all). Can the cluster handle this? Can it detect the mismatch and rebuild correctly?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For extra chaos, there&#x27;s also &lt;code&gt;RebootAndDelete&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; which gives the machine &lt;strong&gt;brand new empty folders&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. No data. Fresh disks. This tests the actual failure mode of replacing a dead drive or provisioning a new machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read that again. During testing, FoundationDB &lt;strong&gt;randomly swaps or deletes storage server data on reboot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If your distributed database doesn&#x27;t assume storage servers occasionally come back with amnesia or someone else&#x27;s memories, you&#x27;re not testing the real world. Because surely, no one has ever accidentally mounted the wrong volume in a Kubernetes deployment, right?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you get from all this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real cluster behavior&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Coordinators elect leaders, transaction logs replicate commits, storage servers handle reads&#x2F;writes, backup agents run&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real failure modes&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Process crashes, machine reboots, network partitions (via &lt;code&gt;g_clogging&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;), slow disks (via &lt;code&gt;AsyncFileNonDurable&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;), disk swaps, data loss&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realistic topologies&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Multi-region configurations, different storage engines, different replication modes, different machine counts&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you run a simulation test, SimulatedCluster boots this entire virtual cluster, lets it stabilize, runs workloads against it while injecting chaos, then validates correctness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;workloads-stress-testing-under-chaos&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#workloads-stress-testing-under-chaos&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: workloads-stress-testing-under-chaos&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Workloads: Stress Testing Under Chaos&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;30 seconds. 2500 transactions per second. Concurrent machines swapping edges in a distributed data structure while chaos engines inject failures. Let&#x27;s see if the database survives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;Simulation Overview
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;┌────────────┬──────────────────┬────────────────┬─────────────────┬────────────────┐
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ Seed       ┆ Replication      ┆ Simulated Time ┆ Real Time       ┆ Storage Engine │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;╞════════════╪══════════════════╪════════════════╪═════════════════╪════════════════╡
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 1876983470 ┆ triple           ┆ 5m 47s         ┆ 18s 891ms       ┆ ssd-2          │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;└────────────┴──────────────────┴────────────────┴─────────────────┴────────────────┘
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Timeline of Chaos Events
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;┌──────────┬────────────────────┬──────────────────────────────────────┐
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ Time (s) ┆ Event Type         ┆ Details                              │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;╞══════════╪════════════════════╪══════════════════════════════════════╡
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 87.234   ┆ Coordinator Change ┆ Triggering leader election           │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 92.156   ┆ Process Reboot     ┆ KillInstantly process at 10.0.4.2:3  │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 92.156   ┆ Process Reboot     ┆ KillInstantly process at 10.0.4.2:1  │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 95.871   ┆ Coordinator Change ┆ Triggering leader election           │
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 103.445  ┆ Process Reboot     ┆ RebootAndDelete process at 10.0.2.1:4│
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;│ 103.445  ┆ Process Reboot     ┆ RebootAndDelete process at 10.0.2.1:2│
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;└──────────┴────────────────────┴──────────────────────────────────────┘
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Chaos Summary
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  Network Partitions: 187 events (max duration: 5.2s)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  Process Kills: 2 KillInstantly, 2 RebootAndDelete
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  Coordinator Changes: 2
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The cluster survived.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; 187 network partitions. 4 process kills. 2 coordinator changes. 5 minutes of simulated time compressed into 18 seconds of wall-clock time. Every transaction completed correctly. The cycle invariant never broke.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did we unleash this chaos? Here&#x27;s the test configuration:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;toml&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-toml &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-toml&quot; data-lang=&quot;toml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[configuration]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buggify &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;minimumReplication &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[[test]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testTitle &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;CycleWithAttrition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;transactionsPerSecond &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2500.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Rollback&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-just-happened&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-just-happened&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-just-happened&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;What Just Happened?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four concurrent workloads ran on the same simulated cluster for 30 seconds. &lt;strong&gt;Workloads&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; are reusable scenario templates (180+ built-in in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;tree&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&quot;&gt;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) that either generate transactions or inject chaos.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The application workload&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; we ran:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;Cycle.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;Cycle.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;): Hammered the database with 2500 transactions&#x2F;second, each one swapping edges in a distributed graph. Tests SERIALIZABLE isolation by maintaining a cycle invariant. If isolation breaks, the cycle splits or nodes vanish. We&#x27;ll dive deep into how this works below.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The chaos workloads&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; that tried to break it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;RandomClogging.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;RandomClogging.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;): Calls &lt;code&gt;g_simulator-&amp;gt;clogInterface(ip, duration)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to partition machines. Those &lt;strong&gt;187 network partitions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; we saw? This workload. Some lasted over 5 seconds.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;MachineAttrition.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;MachineAttrition.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;): Calls &lt;code&gt;g_simulator-&amp;gt;killMachine()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;g_simulator-&amp;gt;rebootMachine()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;4 process kills&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (2 instant, 2 with deleted data)? This workload.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rollback&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;Rollback.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;Rollback.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;): Forces proxy-to-TLog failures, triggering coordinator recovery. The &lt;strong&gt;2 coordinator changes&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;? This workload.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workloads are composable. The TOML format lets you stack them: &lt;code&gt;[configuration]&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; sets global parameters (BUGGIFY, replication), each &lt;code&gt;[[test.workload]]&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; adds another concurrent workload. Want to test atomic operations under network partitions? Stack &lt;code&gt;AtomicOps&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Want to test backup during machine failures? Combine &lt;code&gt;BackupToBlob&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Test files live in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;tree&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;tests&quot;&gt;tests&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-cycle-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#how-does-cycle-work&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: how-does-cycle-work&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;How Does Cycle Work?&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that test we just ran? Let&#x27;s break down how the &lt;code&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; workload actually works. It creates a directed graph where every node points to exactly one other node, forming a single cycle: &lt;code&gt;0→1→2→...→N→0&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Then it runs 2500 concurrent transactions per second, each one randomly swapping edges in the graph. Meanwhile, chaos workloads kill machines, partition the network, and force coordinator changes. &lt;strong&gt;If SERIALIZABLE isolation works correctly, the cycle never breaks&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. You always have exactly N nodes in one ring, never split cycles or dangling pointers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every workload implements four phases (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;include&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;workloads.actor.h&quot;&gt;workloads.actor.h&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SETUP&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;Cycle.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;Cycle.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;): Creates &lt;code&gt;nodeCount&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; nodes. Each key stores the index of the next node in the cycle. Key 0 → value 1, key 1 → value 2, ..., key N-1 → value 0.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EXECUTION&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Multiple concurrent &lt;code&gt;cycleClient&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; actors run this loop:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick random node &lt;code&gt;r&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read three hops: &lt;code&gt;r→r2→r3→r4&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swap the middle two edges: make &lt;code&gt;r→r3&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;r2→r4&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transaction reads 3 keys and writes 2. If isolation breaks, you could create cycles of the wrong length or lose nodes entirely.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHECK&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: One client reads the entire graph in a single transaction. Starting from node 0, follow pointers: 0→next→next→next. Count the hops. After exactly &lt;code&gt;nodeCount&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; hops, you must be back at node 0. If you get there earlier (cycle too short) or can&#x27;t get there (broken chain), the test fails. Also verifies transaction throughput met the expected rate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;METRICS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Reports transactions completed, retry counts, latency percentiles.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the pattern all workloads follow: SETUP initializes data, EXECUTION generates load, CHECK verifies correctness, METRICS reports results. When you execute a test, SimulatedCluster boots the cluster, runs SETUP phases sequentially, then runs all EXECUTION phases concurrently (they&#x27;re Flow actors on the same event loop). After &lt;code&gt;testDuration&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, CHECK phases verify correctness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is what runs before every FoundationDB commit.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Not once. Not a few times. Thousands of test runs with different seeds, different cluster configurations, different workload combinations. Application workloads generate realistic transactions. Chaos workloads inject failures. The CHECK phases prove correctness survived the chaos. This is why FoundationDB doesn&#x27;t fail in production. The simulator has already broken it every possible way, and every bug got fixed before shipping.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generated that simulation output using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-sim-visualizer&quot;&gt;fdb-sim-visualizer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a tool I wrote to parse simulation trace logs and understand what happened during testing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;verifying-correctness-building-reliable-workloads&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#verifying-correctness-building-reliable-workloads&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: verifying-correctness-building-reliable-workloads&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Verifying Correctness: Building Reliable Workloads&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But here&#x27;s the hard part: proving correctness when everything is randomized.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The cluster survived. Transactions completed. The cycle invariant never broke... or did it? When you&#x27;re running 2500 transactions per second with random edge swaps under 187 network partitions, how do you &lt;strong&gt;prove&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; nothing went wrong? You can&#x27;t just check if the database &quot;looks okay.&quot; You need &lt;strong&gt;proof&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; the invariants held.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB&#x27;s approach: &lt;strong&gt;track during EXECUTION, verify in CHECK.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Three patterns emerge across the codebase:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pattern-1-reference-implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#pattern-1-reference-implementation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: pattern-1-reference-implementation&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Pattern 1: Reference Implementation&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The challenge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: How do you verify complex API behavior under chaos?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The solution&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Run every operation twice. &lt;code&gt;ApiCorrectness&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;ApiCorrectness.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;ApiCorrectness.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) mirrors all operations in a simple &lt;code&gt;MemoryKeyValueStore&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (just a &lt;code&gt;std::map&amp;lt;Key, Value&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). Every &lt;code&gt;transaction-&amp;gt;set(k, v)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; also executes &lt;code&gt;store.set(k, v)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; in memory. The CHECK phase reads from FDB and compares with the memory model. Mismatch = bug found.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pattern-2-operation-logging&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#pattern-2-operation-logging&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: pattern-2-operation-logging&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Pattern 2: Operation Logging&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The challenge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: How do you verify atomic operations executed in the right order?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The solution&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Log everything. &lt;code&gt;AtomicOps&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;AtomicOps.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;AtomicOps.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) logs every operation to a separate keyspace. During EXECUTION: &lt;code&gt;atomicOp(ops_key, value)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; on real data, &lt;code&gt;set(log_key, value)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to track what happened. During CHECK: replay all logged operations, compute what the final state should be, compare with actual database state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pattern-3-invariant-tracking&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#pattern-3-invariant-tracking&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: pattern-3-invariant-tracking&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Pattern 3: Invariant Tracking&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The challenge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: How do you prove SERIALIZABLE isolation worked during chaos?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The solution&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Maintain a mathematical invariant that breaks if isolation fails. &lt;code&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (from our test earlier) maintains &quot;exactly N nodes in one ring.&quot; During EXECUTION, random edge swaps must preserve the invariant. During CHECK, walk the graph: 0→next→next→next. After exactly N hops, you must be back at node 0. If you arrive earlier (cycle split) or can&#x27;t arrive (broken chain), isolation failed. The CHECK phase catches this immediately.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-clientid-for-work-distribution&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#using-clientid-for-work-distribution&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: using-clientid-for-work-distribution&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Using clientId for Work Distribution&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every workload gets &lt;code&gt;clientId&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (0, 1, 2...) and &lt;code&gt;clientCount&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (total clients). Three patterns:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client 0 only&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;AtomicOps.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;AtomicOps.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(clientId != &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;return &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Common for CHECK phases
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partition keyspace&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;WatchAndWait.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;WatchAndWait.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;uint64_t startNode = (nodeCount * clientId) &#x2F; clientCount;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;uint64_t endNode = (nodeCount * (clientId + &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)) &#x2F; clientCount;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Client 0: nodes 0-33, Client 1: nodes 34-66, Client 2: nodes 67-99
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round-robin&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;workloads&#x2F;Watches.actor.cpp&quot;&gt;Watches.actor.cpp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(i % clientCount == clientId)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Client 0: keys 0,3,6,9... Client 1: keys 1,4,7,10...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;clientId&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to create concurrency (multiple clients hitting different keys) or coordinate work (one client checks, others generate load).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;randomize-everything&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#randomize-everything&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: randomize-everything&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Randomize Everything&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to finding bugs: &lt;strong&gt;randomize every decision&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Which keys to read? Random. How many operations per transaction? Random. Which atomic operation type? Random. Order of operations? Random. When to inject chaos? Random.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But use &lt;code&gt;deterministicRandom()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; for all randomness. It&#x27;s a seeded PRNG. Same seed = same random choices = reproducible failures. When a test fails after 10 million operations, rerun with the same seed, get the exact same failure at the exact same point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pattern-selection-guide&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#pattern-selection-guide&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: pattern-selection-guide&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Pattern Selection Guide&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Testing&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Use Pattern&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Example Workload&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;API correctness&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Reference implementation&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;ApiCorrectness&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Atomic operations&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Operation logging&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;AtomicOps&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;ACID guarantees&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Invariant tracking&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Backup&#x2F;restore&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Absence checking&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;BackupCorrectness&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaos workloads (&lt;code&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Rollback&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) don&#x27;t need CHECK phases. They just return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. They inject failures. Application workloads verify that correctness survived the chaos.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-workloads-in-rust&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#writing-workloads-in-rust&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: writing-workloads-in-rust&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Writing Workloads in Rust&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember those chaos workloads hammering the Cycle test? &lt;code&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Rollback&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. All written in C++ Flow. But you can write workloads in &lt;strong&gt;Rust&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and compile them directly into the simulator. At Clever Cloud, we open-sourced &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;tree&#x2F;main&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&quot;&gt;foundationdb-simulation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which lets you implement the &lt;code&gt;RustWorkload&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; trait with &lt;code&gt;setup()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;start()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;check()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; methods using Rust&#x27;s async&#x2F;await:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;#[&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;async_trait&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;impl &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;RustWorkload &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;MyWorkload {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;setup&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Database, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;_ctx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Context) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;()&amp;gt; {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Initialize test data
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        db.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;run&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(|&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, _| async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;move &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            tx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;set&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;key&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;value&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        }).await
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;start&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Database, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Context) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;()&amp;gt; {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Generate load under simulation
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;_ in &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..ctx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;get_option&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;nodeCount&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            db.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;run&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(|&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, _| async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;move &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; value = tx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;get&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;key&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;false&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;).await?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Your workload logic here
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            }).await?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;check&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Database, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;_ctx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Context) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;()&amp;gt; {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Verify correctness after chaos
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your Rust code compiles to a shared library, FDB&#x27;s &lt;code&gt;ExternalWorkload&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; loads it at runtime via FFI, and your Rust async functions run on the same Flow event loop as the C++ cluster. The FFI boundary is managed by the &lt;code&gt;foundationdb-simulation&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; crate, which handles marshaling between Flow&#x27;s event loop and Rust futures. Same determinism, same reproducibility, same chaos injection. But you&#x27;re writing &lt;code&gt;async fn&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;ACTOR Future&amp;lt;Void&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&#x2F;examples&#x2F;atomic&#x2F;lib.rs&quot;&gt;complete example workload&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; testing atomic operations in ~100 lines of Rust.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;simulation-at-clever-cloud-building-materia&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#simulation-at-clever-cloud-building-materia&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: simulation-at-clever-cloud-building-materia&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Simulation at Clever Cloud: Building Materia&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Clever Cloud, we use simulation to build &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;features&#x2F;2024&#x2F;06&#x2F;11&#x2F;materia-kv-our-easy-to-use-serverless-key-value-database-is-available-to-all&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Materia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, our serverless database products. I&#x27;m the lead engineer behind Materia and the main maintainer of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&quot;&gt;foundationdb-rs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built a Rust SDK on top of FDB, similar to Apple&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;FoundationDB&#x2F;fdb-record-layer&quot;&gt;Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It provides structured records, secondary indexes, query planning, and multi-tenant isolation. The result: a distributed transactional database built on FoundationDB&#x27;s guarantees.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB is a hidden technology: you don&#x27;t use it directly, you build layers on top. But here&#x27;s the trick: &lt;strong&gt;patterns like index design, quota management, and schema management should be written once and consumed, not reimplemented in every product&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Our SDK abstracts these patterns. Need secondary indexes? The SDK handles keyspace layout, index updates, and query planning. Need multi-tenant isolation? The SDK provides it. Need quota enforcement or permission management? &lt;strong&gt;We built a common control plane that works across all products&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; built on the SDK. Write the hard distributed systems logic once, simulate it until it&#x27;s bulletproof, then reuse it everywhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every merge request runs simulation tests in CI. We test SDK scenarios (indexing, query planning) and full product workloads under chaos. Multi-tenant isolation, concurrent queries, network partitions, machine crashes. The bugs we catch vary by layer. SDK changes catch nasty bugs like duplicated indexes during &lt;code&gt;maybe_committed&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; transactions. Product changes catch simpler errors like accidentally blocking FDB&#x27;s retry logic or breaking atomicity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the real value isn&#x27;t just bug detection. &lt;strong&gt;Instead of writing hundreds of unit tests, we write workloads that fuzz our code under chaos.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; One workload with randomized operations and deterministic chaos replaces dozens of hand-crafted test cases. When engineers write workloads for their features, they&#x27;re forced to think: &quot;What happens when this retries during a partition?&quot; &quot;How do I verify correctness when transactions can commit in any order?&quot; &lt;strong&gt;Designing for chaos&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; becomes natural. The act of writing simulation workloads improves the design itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The confidence this gives a small team is extraordinary. When you can prove your code survives hundreds of network partitions and machine crashes before shipping, you sleep better at night. Our latest layer, an etcd-compatible API for managed Kubernetes, was built from the ground up with simulation in mind. We&#x27;re even &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;issues&#x2F;12343&quot;&gt;contributing features back to FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to better support layers like ours.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it survives simulation, it survives production.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-simulations-yourself&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#running-simulations-yourself&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: running-simulations-yourself&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Running Simulations Yourself&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think you can break FoundationDB? You don&#x27;t need to build from source or set up a cluster. Download a prebuilt &lt;code&gt;fdbserver&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; binary from the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;releases&quot;&gt;releases page&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, create a test file, and unleash chaos:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Download fdbserver (Linux example, adjust for your platform)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;wget&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;releases&#x2F;download&#x2F;7.3.27&#x2F;fdbserver.x86_64
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;chmod&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; +x fdbserver.x86_64
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Create the folder for traces
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;mkdir&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; events
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Run a simulation test with JSON trace output
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;.&#x2F;fdbserver.x86_64 -r&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; simulation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; -f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Attritions.toml&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --trace-format&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; json&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; -L&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; .&#x2F;events&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --logsize&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 1GiB
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two test files to get you started. Save either as a &lt;code&gt;.toml&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file and run with the command above.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attritions.toml&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - Network partitions + machine crashes + database reconfigurations (the NemesisTest shown earlier):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;toml&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-toml &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-toml&quot; data-lang=&quot;toml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[configuration]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buggify &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;minimumReplication &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[[test]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testTitle &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;NemesisTest&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ReadWrite&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;transactionsPerSecond &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RandomClogging&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Network partitions
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;swizzle &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Unclog in reversed order
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Attrition&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Machine crashes
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Rollback&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Proxy-to-TLog errors
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ChangeConfig&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Database reconfigurations
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;coordinators &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;auto&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DiskFailureCycle.toml&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - Disk failures + bit flips during the Cycle workload:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;toml&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-toml &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-toml&quot; data-lang=&quot;toml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[configuration]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;minimumReplication &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;minimumRegions &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[[test]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testTitle &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;DiskFailureCycle&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Cycle&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;transactionsPerSecond &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2500.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    [[test.workload]]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testName &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;DiskFailureInjection&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;testDuration &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;120.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;stallInterval &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;5.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;stallPeriod &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;5.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;throttlePeriod &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;corruptFile &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;percentBitFlips &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulation generates JSON trace logs in &lt;code&gt;.&#x2F;events&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Parse them with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-sim-visualizer&quot;&gt;fdb-sim-visualizer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more test examples, check FoundationDB&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;tree&#x2F;dfbb0ea72ce01ba87148ef67cf216200e8b249cd&#x2F;tests&quot;&gt;tests&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; directory. Hundreds of workload combinations testing every corner of the system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-ve-never-been-woken-up-by-fdb&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why-i-ve-never-been-woken-up-by-fdb&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why-i-ve-never-been-woken-up-by-fdb&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Why I&#x27;ve Never Been Woken Up by FDB&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After years of on-call and one trillion CPU-hours of simulation, I&#x27;ve never been woken up by FoundationDB. Now you know why.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interface swapping lets the same code run in both production and simulation. Flow actors enable single-threaded determinism. The event loop compresses years into seconds. BUGGIFY injects chaos into every corner of the codebase. SimulatedCluster builds entire distributed systems in memory. Workloads generate realistic transactions while chaos engines try to break everything. And deterministic randomness guarantees every bug can be reproduced, diagnosed, and fixed before shipping.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simulator has already broken FoundationDB in every possible way. Network partitions during coordinator elections. Machine crashes mid-transaction. Disks swapped between nodes on reboot. Bit flips. Slow I&#x2F;O. Every edge case, every race condition, every distributed systems nightmare. Found, fixed, and verified before production ever sees it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Want to try breaking FoundationDB yourself?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Grab a test config from above, run the simulator, inject chaos, and see if you can find a bug that survived one trillion CPU-hours. If you do, the FDB team would love to hear about it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out with any questions or to share your simulation testing experiences or FDB workloads. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">testing</category>
          <category domain="tag">simulation</category>
          <category domain="tag">deterministic</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed-systems</category>
          <category domain="tag">diving-into</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>From Arc to Box: One Deref Bound to Rule Them All</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/from-arc-to-box-one-deref-bound/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/from-arc-to-box-one-deref-bound/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/from-arc-to-box-one-deref-bound/">&lt;p&gt;While working on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&quot;&gt;FoundationDB-rs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I hit a design problem that seemed like it would require complex trait gymnastics. I had two transaction types with identical APIs but different ownership semantics, and I needed functions to accept both. The solution turned out to be embarrassingly simple. It was already implemented.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem-two-transaction-types-one-api&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-problem-two-transaction-types-one-api&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-problem-two-transaction-types-one-api&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Problem: Two Transaction Types, One API&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB-rs has two transaction types that do exactly the same thing but with different ownership models:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;pub struct &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Transaction {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;inner&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: NonNull&amp;lt;fdb_sys::FDBTransaction&amp;gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;metrics&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Option&amp;lt;TransactionMetrics&amp;gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;pub struct &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;RetryableTransaction {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;inner&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Arc&amp;lt;Transaction&amp;gt;,  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Arc needed for retry loop ownership
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why two types?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; FoundationDB requires retry loops for handling conflicts and retriable errors. The &lt;code&gt;Transaction&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is perfect when you&#x27;re managing retries manually or doing single-shot operations. The &lt;code&gt;RetryableTransaction&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; wraps it in an &lt;code&gt;Arc&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; so the automatic retry machinery in &lt;code&gt;Database::run()&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can clone references across async boundaries and exponential backoff delays.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge: users need to write code that works with both. Real FoundationDB applications mix both patterns depending on the use case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-obvious-solutions-didn-t-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-obvious-solutions-didn-t-work&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-obvious-solutions-didn-t-work&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Obvious Solutions Didn&#x27;t Work&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first instinct was creating a trait. But FoundationDB-rs operates directly on raw C pointers (&lt;code&gt;NonNull&amp;lt;fdb_sys::FDBTransaction&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) with custom &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; implementations that handle FFI complexity and error mapping. Writing a trait with async methods that return these custom futures means associated types, lifetime bounds, and complex error handling. The resulting trait becomes painful to use and understand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered an enum wrapper:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;enum &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;AnyTransaction&amp;lt;&amp;#39;a&amp;gt; {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    Regular(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;a&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Transaction),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    Retryable(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;a&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; RetryableTransaction),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this felt wrong. Users would need to match everywhere, and it adds runtime overhead for what should be a compile-time decision. Plus it doesn&#x27;t feel natural to use.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-accidental-solution&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-accidental-solution&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-accidental-solution&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Accidental Solution&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;RetryableTransaction&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; already had this implementation for convenience:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;impl &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Deref &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;for &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;RetryableTransaction {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;type &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Target = Transaction;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;deref&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) -&amp;gt; &amp;amp;Transaction {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.inner.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;deref&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d added this so users could call transaction methods directly on &lt;code&gt;RetryableTransaction&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; instances. But this &lt;strong&gt;accidentally solved the entire design problem.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Functions can accept both types through a simple generic bound:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;perform_operations&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &amp;amp;T) -&amp;gt; FdbResult&amp;lt;()&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;where
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    T: Deref&amp;lt;Target = Transaction&amp;gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    tx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;set&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;key&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;value&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; value = tx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;get&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;key&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;false&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;).await?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    tx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;clear_range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;start&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;end&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the same function works seamlessly with both transaction types:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Direct transaction usage
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tx = db.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;create_transaction&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;perform_operations&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;tx).await?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Automatic retry loop usage
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;db.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;run&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(|&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;rtx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;| async &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;move &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;perform_operations&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;rtx).await?;  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Same function, no changes needed!
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    Ok(())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}).await?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler handles everything through deref coercion. All methods of &lt;code&gt;Transaction&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; remain directly accessible on both types, and there&#x27;s zero runtime overhead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pattern-arc-deref-universal-apis&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-pattern-arc-deref-universal-apis&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-pattern-arc-deref-universal-apis&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Pattern: Arc&lt;T&gt; + Deref = Universal APIs&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern works whenever you have a type &lt;code&gt;T&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and a wrapper containing &lt;code&gt;Arc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;Box&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Rc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, etc.). As long as the wrapper implements &lt;code&gt;Deref&amp;lt;Target = T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, you can write generic functions that accept both:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Any function with this signature accepts:
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; - &amp;amp;T directly  
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; - &amp;amp;WrapperType where WrapperType: Deref&amp;lt;Target = T&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; - &amp;amp;Arc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;, &amp;amp;Box&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;, &amp;amp;Rc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; (stdlib types already implement Deref)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;use_any_version&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;D&amp;gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;val&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: &amp;amp;D)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;where 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    D: Deref&amp;lt;Target = T&amp;gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    val.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;some_method&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;();  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; All methods of T available through deref coercion
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key insight: when you&#x27;re designing APIs that need to work with both &lt;code&gt;T&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Arc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, don&#x27;t reach for traits or enums. The standard library already solved this. &lt;code&gt;Arc&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; implements &lt;code&gt;Deref&amp;lt;Target = T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, and your custom wrapper types should do the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you implement &lt;code&gt;Deref&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, any function that accepts &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;D where D: Deref&amp;lt;Target = T&amp;gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; automatically works with your owned type, your wrapper type, and any smart pointer containing your type. The compiler handles everything through deref coercion, and you get zero-cost abstraction that feels completely natural to use.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out with any questions or to share your experiences with Deref patterns in Rust. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">rust</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">programming</category>
          <category domain="tag">metaprogramming</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Testing: prevention vs discovery</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/testing-prevention-vs-discovery/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/testing-prevention-vs-discovery/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/testing-prevention-vs-discovery/">&lt;p&gt;While working on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;moonpool&quot;&gt;moonpool&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, my hobby project for studying and backporting FoundationDB&#x27;s low-level engineering concepts (actor model, deterministic simulation, network fault injection), Claude Code did something remarkable: it found a bug I didn&#x27;t know existed on its own. Not through traditional testing, but through active exploration of edge cases I hadn&#x27;t considered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;testing-prevention-vs-discovery&#x2F;claude-moonpool.png&quot; alt=&quot;Claude Code autonomously debugging moonpool&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude identified a faulty seed triggering an edge case, debugged it locally using deterministic replay, and added it to the test suite. All by itself. 🤯 &lt;strong&gt;This wasn&#x27;t prevention but discovery.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; It&#x27;s time to shift our testing paradigm from preventing regressions to actively discovering unknown bugs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-for-discovery&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#building-for-discovery&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: building-for-discovery&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Building for Discovery&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between prevention and discovery isn&#x27;t just philosophical but requires completely different system design. Moonpool was built from day one around three principles that enable active bug discovery:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deterministic simulation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Every execution is completely reproducible. Given the same seed, the system makes identical decisions every time. This changes debugging from &quot;I can&#x27;t reproduce this&quot; to &quot;let me replay exactly what happened.&quot; More importantly, it lets LLMs explore the state space step by step without getting lost in non-deterministic noise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controlled failure injection&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Built-in mechanisms intentionally introduce failures in controlled, reproducible ways. This includes timed failures like network delays and disconnects, plus &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;transactional.blog&#x2F;simulation&#x2F;buggify&quot;&gt;&quot;buggify&quot; mechanisms&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that inject faulty internal state at strategic points in the code. Each buggify point is either enabled or disabled for an entire simulation run, creating consistent failure scenarios instead of random chaos. Instead of waiting for production to reveal edge cases, we force the system to encounter dangerous, bug-finding behaviors during development.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observability through sometimes assertions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Borrowed from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;antithesis.com&#x2F;docs&#x2F;best_practices&#x2F;sometimes_assertions&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Antithesis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, these verify we&#x27;re actually discovering the edge cases we think we&#x27;re testing. Here&#x27;s what they look like:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Verify that server binds sometimes fail during chaos testing
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sometimes_assert!(
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    server_bind_fails,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.bind_result.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;is_err&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Server bind should sometimes fail during chaos testing&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Ensure message queues sometimes approach capacity under load
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;sometimes_assert!(
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    peer_queue_near_capacity,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    state.send_queue.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;len&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() &amp;gt;= (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.config.max_queue_size as &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;f64 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;* &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.8&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) as &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;usize&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Message queue should sometimes approach capacity limit&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional code coverage only tells you &quot;this line was reached.&quot; Sometimes assertions verify &quot;this interesting scenario actually happened.&quot; If a sometimes assertion never triggers across thousands of test runs, you know you&#x27;re not discovering the edge cases that matter.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three elements shift testing from prevention to discovery. Instead of developers writing tests for scenarios they already know about, the system forces them to hit failure modes they haven&#x27;t thought of. For Claude, this meant it could explore the state space step by step, understanding not just what the code does, but what breaks it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-chaos-environment&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-chaos-environment&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-chaos-environment&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Chaos Environment&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moonpool is currently limited to simulating TCP connections through its Peer abstraction, but even this narrow scope creates a surprisingly rich failure environment. Here&#x27;s what the chaos testing configuration looks like (borrowed from TigerBeetle&#x27;s approach):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;impl &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;NetworkRandomizationRanges {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F;&#x2F; Create chaos testing ranges with connection cutting enabled for distributed systems testing
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;pub fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;chaos_testing&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;() -&amp;gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;Self &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;Self &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            bind_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;200&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                       &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 10-200µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            bind_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                     &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 10-100µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            accept_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 1-10ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            accept_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;15000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,               &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 1-15ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            connect_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;50000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 1-50ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            connect_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;5000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,             &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 5-100ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            read_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                        &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 5-100µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            read_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;200&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                     &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 10-200µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            write_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;50&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                     &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 50-1000µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            write_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;2000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 100-2000µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            clogging_probability_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.3&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,           &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 10-30% chance of temporary network congestion
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            clogging_base_duration_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;50000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;300000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 50-300ms congestion duration in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            clogging_jitter_duration_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;400000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 100-400ms additional congestion variance in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            cutting_probability_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.10&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0.20&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,          &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 10-20% cutting chance per tick
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            cutting_reconnect_base_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;200000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;800000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,   &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 200-800ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            cutting_reconnect_jitter_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;100000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;500000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 100-500ms in µs
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;            cutting_max_cuts_range: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;..&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,                   &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 1-2 cuts per connection max (exclusive upper bound)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with just TCP simulation, this creates a hostile environment where connections randomly fail, messages get delayed, and network operations experience unpredictable latencies. Each seed represents a different combination of timing and probability, creating unique failure scenarios.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-even-simple-network-code-needs-chaos&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why-even-simple-network-code-needs-chaos&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why-even-simple-network-code-needs-chaos&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Why Even Simple Network Code Needs Chaos&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think testing a simple peer implementation with fault injection is overkill, but production experience and research show otherwise. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.usenix.org&#x2F;system&#x2F;files&#x2F;osdi18-alquraan.pdf&quot;&gt;&quot;An Analysis of Network-Partitioning Failures in Cloud Systems&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (OSDI &#x27;18) studied real-world failures and found:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;80%&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of network partition failures have catastrophic impact&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;27%&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; lead to data loss (the most common consequence)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;90%&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of these failures are silent&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21%&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; cause permanent damage that persists even after the partition heals&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;83%&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; need three additional events to manifest&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last point is crucial; exactly the kind of complex interaction that deterministic simulation with fault injection helps uncover.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My peer implementation only does simple ping-pong communication, yet it still took some work to make it robust enough to pass all the checks and assertions. It&#x27;s enough complexity for Claude to discover edge cases in connection handling, retry logic, and recovery mechanisms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breakthrough wasn&#x27;t that Claude wrote perfect code but that &lt;strong&gt;Claude could discover and explore failure scenarios I hadn&#x27;t thought to test, then use deterministic replay to debug and fix what went wrong.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-paradigm-shift&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-paradigm-shift&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-paradigm-shift&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Paradigm Shift&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between prevention and discovery completely changes how we think about software quality. &lt;strong&gt;Prevention testing asks &quot;did we break what used to work?&quot; Discovery testing asks &quot;what else is broken that we haven&#x27;t found yet?&quot;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shift creates a powerful feedback loop for young engineers and LLMs alike. Both developers and LLMs learn what production failure really looks like, not the sanitized version we imagine. When Claude can explore failure scenarios step by step and immediately see the results through sometimes assertions, it becomes a discovery partner that finds edge cases human intuition misses.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t theoretical. It&#x27;s working in my hobby project today. Moonpool is definitely hobby-grade, but if a side project can enable LLM-assisted bug discovery, imagine what&#x27;s possible with production systems designed from the ground up for deterministic testing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tigerbeetle.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TigerBeetle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;antithesis.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Antithesis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; communities have been practicing discovery-oriented testing for years. FoundationDB&#x27;s legendary reliability comes from exactly this approach; deterministic simulation that actively hunts for bugs rather than just preventing regressions. After operating FoundationDB in production for 3 years, I can confirm it&#x27;s by far the most robust and predictable distributed system I&#x27;ve encountered. Everything behaves exactly as documented, with none of the usual distributed systems surprises. I&#x27;ve written more about these ideas in my posts on &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;simulation-driven-development&#x2F;&quot;&gt;simulation-driven development&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;&quot;&gt;notes about FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#x27;s new is that LLMs can now participate in this process.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Through deterministic simulation and sometimes assertions, we&#x27;re not just telling the LLM &quot;write good code&quot; but showing it exactly what production failure looks like. If you&#x27;re curious about production-grade implementations of these ideas, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;antithesis.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Antithesis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;; their best hidden feature is that it works on any existing system without requiring a rewrite.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tools exist. The techniques are proven. &lt;strong&gt;Testing must evolve from prevention to discovery.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The future isn&#x27;t about writing better test cases but about building systems that actively reveal their own bugs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out with any questions or to share your experiences with deterministic testing. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">testing</category>
          <category domain="tag">simulation</category>
          <category domain="tag">deterministic</category>
          <category domain="tag">llm</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Bypassing FoundationDB&#x27;s Transaction Limits with Record Layer Continuations</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/understanding-fdb-record-layer-continuations/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/understanding-fdb-record-layer-continuations/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/understanding-fdb-record-layer-continuations/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-the-foundationdb-record-layer&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introducing-the-foundationdb-record-layer&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: introducing-the-foundationdb-record-layer&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Introducing the FoundationDB Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the specifics of handling large operations with continuations (the main topic of this post), let&#x27;s briefly introduce the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;foundationdb.github.io&#x2F;fdb-record-layer&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FoundationDB Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It&#x27;s a powerful open-source library built atop FoundationDB that brings a structured, record-oriented data model to FDB&#x27;s highly scalable key-value store. Think of it as adding schema management, rich indexing capabilities, and a sophisticated query engine, making it easier to build complex applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Record Layer is versatile and has been adopted for demanding use-cases, most notably by Apple as the core of CloudKit, powering services for millions of users. It allows developers to define their data models using Protocol Buffers and then query them in a flexible manner.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, you can express queries like finding all &#x27;Order&#x27; records for roses costing less than $50 with a declarative API (example in Java):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;java&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-java &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;RecordQuery&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; query = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;RecordQuery&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;newBuilder&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;setRecordType&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Order&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;setFilter&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Query&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Query&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;field&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;price&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;).&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;lessThan&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;50&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;),
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;                &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Query&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;field&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;flower&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;).&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;matches&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Query&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;field&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;).&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;equalsValue&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;FlowerType&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;ROSE&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;name&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()))))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        .&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;build&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;();
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started and explore its capabilities further, the official &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;foundationdb.github.io&#x2F;fdb-record-layer&#x2F;GettingStarted.html&quot;&gt;Getting Started Guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is an excellent resource. You can also watch these talks for a deeper understanding:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=SvoUHHM9IKU&quot;&gt;Using FoundationDB and the FDB Record Layer to Build CloudKit - Scott Gray, Apple&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=HLE8chgw6LI&quot;&gt;FoundationDB Record Layer: Open Source Structured Storage on FoundationDB - Nicholas Schiefer, Apple&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed academic perspective on its design and how CloudKit uses it, refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.foundationdb.org&#x2F;files&#x2F;record-layer-paper.pdf&quot;&gt;SIGMOD&#x27;19 paper: FoundationDB Record Layer: A Multi-Tenant Structured Datastore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenge-fdb-s-transaction-constraints&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-challenge-fdb-s-transaction-constraints&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-challenge-fdb-s-transaction-constraints&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Challenge: FDB&#x27;s Transaction Constraints&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB (FDB) imposes strict constraints on its transactions: they must complete within 5 seconds and are limited to 10MB of manipulated data, either writes or reads. These constraints are fundamental to FDB&#x27;s design, ensuring high performance and serializable isolation. However, they pose a significant challenge for operations that inherently require processing large datasets or executing complex queries that cannot complete within these tight boundaries, such as full table scans, large analytical queries, or bulk data exports.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;FoundationDB Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; addresses this challenge through a mechanism known as &lt;strong&gt;continuations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Continuations allow a single logical operation to be broken down into a sequence of smaller, independent FDB transactions. Each transaction processes a segment of the total workload and, if more work remains, yields a &lt;strong&gt;continuation token&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. This opaque token encapsulates the state required to resume the operation precisely where the previous transaction left off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article delves into the technical details of Record Layer continuations, exploring how they function and how to leverage them effectively to build robust, scalable applications on FDB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bridging-transactions-the-role-of-continuations&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#bridging-transactions-the-role-of-continuations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: bridging-transactions-the-role-of-continuations&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Bridging Transactions: The Role of Continuations&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a query to retrieve all records matching a specific filter from a large dataset. Executing this as a single FDB transaction would likely violate the 5-second or 10MB limit. The Record Layer employs continuations to serialize this operation across multiple transactions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initial Request:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The application initiates a query against the Record Layer.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Segmented Execution:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The Record Layer&#x27;s query planner executes the query, but with built-in scan limiters. It processes records until a predefined limit (e.g., row count, time duration, or byte size) is approached, or it nears FDB&#x27;s intrinsic transaction limits.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Serialization:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Before the current FDB transaction commits, if the logical operation is incomplete, the Record Layer serializes the execution state of the query plan into a continuation token.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partial Result &amp;amp; Token:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The application receives the processed segment of data and the continuation token. The FDB transaction for this segment commits successfully.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resumption:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; To fetch the next segment, the application submits a new request, providing the previously received continuation token.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Deserialization &amp;amp; Continued Execution:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The Record Layer deserializes the token, restores the query plan&#x27;s state, and resumes execution from the exact point it paused. This typically involves adjusting scan boundaries (e.g., starting a key-range scan from the key after the last one processed).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cycle repeats until the entire logical operation is complete. The continuation token acts as the critical link, enabling a series of short, FDB-compliant transactions to collectively achieve the effect of a single, long-running operation without violating FDB&#x27;s core constraints.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dissecting-the-continuation-token&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#dissecting-the-continuation-token&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: dissecting-the-continuation-token&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Dissecting the Continuation Token&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the continuation token is &lt;strong&gt;opaque&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to the application (it&#x27;s a &lt;code&gt;byte[]&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; that should not be introspected or modified), it internally contains structured information vital for resuming query execution. The exact format is an implementation detail of the Record Layer and can evolve, but conceptually, it must capture:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scan Boundaries:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The key (or keys, for multi-dimensional indexes) where the next scan segment should begin. This ensures no data is missed or re-processed unnecessarily.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Query Plan State:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; For complex query plans involving joins, filters, aggregations, or in-memory sorting, the token may need to store intermediate state specific to those operators. For instance, a &lt;code&gt;UnionPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;IntersectionPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; might need to remember which child plan was active and its respective continuation.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scan Limiter State:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Information about accumulated counts or sizes if the scan was paused due to application-defined limits rather than FDB limits.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version Information:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; To ensure compatibility if the token format changes across Record Layer versions.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opacity of the token is a deliberate design choice. It decouples the application from the internal mechanics of the Record Layer, allowing the latter to evolve its continuation strategies (e.g., for efficiency or new features) without breaking client applications. The application&#x27;s responsibility is solely to store and return this token verbatim.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resuming-query-execution-via-continuations&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#resuming-query-execution-via-continuations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: resuming-query-execution-via-continuations&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Resuming Query Execution via Continuations&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a continuation token is provided to a &lt;code&gt;RecordCursor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (the Record Layer&#x27;s abstraction for iterating over query results), the underlying &lt;code&gt;RecordQueryPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; uses it to reconstruct its state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan Identification:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The token typically identifies the specific query plan or sub-plan it pertains to.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Restoration:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Each operator in the query plan (e.g., &lt;code&gt;IndexScanPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;FilterPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;SortPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) that can be stateful across transaction boundaries implements logic to initialize itself from the continuation. For an &lt;code&gt;IndexScanPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, this primarily means setting the &lt;code&gt;ScanComparisons&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; for the next range read. For a &lt;code&gt;UnionPlan&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, it might mean restoring the continuation for one of its child plans and indicating which child to resume.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Execution Resumption:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Once the plan&#x27;s state is restored, the &lt;code&gt;RecordCursor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can proceed to fetch the next batch of records. The execution effectively &quot;jumps&quot; to the point encoded in the continuation.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mechanism allows the Record Layer to transparently manage the complexities of distributed, stateful iteration over potentially vast datasets, all while adhering to FDB&#x27;s transactional model.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-of-non-atomicity&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#implications-of-non-atomicity&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: implications-of-non-atomicity&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Implications of Non-Atomicity&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s important to understand a key implication of this multi-transaction approach: while each individual FDB transaction executed as part of a continued operation is atomic and isolated (typically providing serializable isolation), the overall logical operation spanning multiple continuations is &lt;strong&gt;not atomic&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in the same way. Mutations to the data by other concurrent transactions can occur &lt;em&gt;between&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the FDB transactions of a continued scan. As a result, a long-running operation that uses continuations doesn&#x27;t see the entire dataset at a single, frozen moment in time. Instead, it might see some data that was present or changed &lt;em&gt;after&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the operation began but &lt;em&gt;before&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it completed. This is a natural consequence of breaking the work into smaller pieces to fit within FDB&#x27;s transaction limits. Applications should be aware of this behavior, particularly if they need all the data to reflect its state from one specific instant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: conclusion&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Record Layer&#x27;s continuation feature is a powerful tool for handling large datasets and complex queries in FoundationDB, but it&#x27;s important to understand the implications of non-atomicity. By breaking operations into smaller, FDB-compliant transactions, the Record Layer provides a flexible and scalable solution while maintaining the core principles of FDB&#x27;s transactional model.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out with any questions or to share your thoughts. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">record-layer</category>
          <category domain="tag">java</category>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">continuation</category>
          <category domain="tag">pagination</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed-systems</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Debugging FoundationDB&#x27;s Data Distributor</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/fdb-data-distributor/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/fdb-data-distributor/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/fdb-data-distributor/">&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB is a powerful, distributed database designed to handle massive workloads with high consistency guarantees. At its core, the &lt;strong&gt;Data Distributor&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; plays a critical role in determining how shards are distributed across the cluster to maintain load balance and resilience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we dive into the &lt;strong&gt;Data Distributor&#x27;s&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; internals, along with practical lessons we learned during a outage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-data-distributor&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-is-the-data-distributor&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-is-the-data-distributor&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;What is the Data Distributor?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Data Distributor (DD)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;architecture.html&quot;&gt;a subsystem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; responsible for efficiently placing and relocating shards (range of keys) in a FoundationDB cluster. Its key goals are:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balancing load across servers&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handling failures by redistributing data&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring optimal data placement for performance reliability&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-distributor-wording&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#data-distributor-wording&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: data-distributor-wording&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Data Distributor wording&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The architecture and behavior of the &lt;strong&gt;Data Distributor&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; are documented in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;release-7.3&#x2F;design&#x2F;data-distributor-internals.md&quot;&gt;official design document&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and introduce the following concepts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: A failure domain in FoundationDB, often considered equivalent to a rack.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shard&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: A range of key-values—essentially a contiguous block of the database keyspace.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Server Team&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: A group of &lt;code&gt;k&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; processes (where &lt;code&gt;k&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is the replication factor) hosting the same shard.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machine Team&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: A collection of &lt;code&gt;k&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; machines, ensuring fault isolation for redundancy.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &quot;machine&quot; in FoundationDB’s documentation &lt;strong&gt;often translates better as &quot;rack&quot;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in many practical cases. Using racks makes the Machine Team&#x27;s role clearer: it ensures fault isolation by storing copies of data in different racks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;debug-dd-with-status-json&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#debug-dd-with-status-json&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: debug-dd-with-status-json&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Debug DD with &lt;code&gt;status json&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your first input point should be to have a look at the &lt;code&gt;team_trackers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; key in the &lt;code&gt;status json&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. The JSON should contain enough information for basic monitoring:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;team_trackers&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: [
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;primary&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;unhealthy_servers&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;state&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;      &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;healthy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;true&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;      &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;name&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;healthy_rebalancing&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  }
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;debug-dd-with-trace-events&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#debug-dd-with-trace-events&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: debug-dd-with-trace-events&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Debug DD with Trace events&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB provides a robust tracing system where each process generates detailed events in either XML or JSON formats. To troubleshoot the &lt;strong&gt;Data Distributor&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, you first need to locate the process it has been elected to. From there, trace events can be analyzed to understand shard movements, priorities, and failures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One particularly important attribute in these events is the &lt;code&gt;Priority&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; field. This field determines the precedence of shard placement or redistribution tasks:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-cpp &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot; data-lang=&quot;cpp&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( PRIORITY_RECOVER_MOVE, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;110 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( PRIORITY_REBALANCE_UNDERUTILIZED_TEAM, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;120 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( PRIORITY_REBALANCE_OVERUTILIZED_TEAM, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;122 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( PRIORITY_TEAM_UNHEALTHY, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;700&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;init&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;( PRIORITY_SPLIT_SHARD, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;950 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full list of defined priorities can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;release-7.3&#x2F;fdbclient&#x2F;ServerKnobs.cpp#L155-L173&quot;&gt;Knobs file&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, providing useful insights into how tasks are scheduled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: Yes, &lt;code&gt;SPLIT_SHARD&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; has an higher priority! See &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;alexmillerdb.bsky.social&#x2F;post&#x2F;3ljsqqvfslc24&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;alexmillerdb.bsky.social&#x2F;post&#x2F;3ljsqqvfslc24&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;serverteaminfo-event&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#serverteaminfo-event&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: serverteaminfo-event&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;code&gt;ServerTeamInfo&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Event&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the state of server teams is essential since the Data Distributor schedules data movements based on real-time metrics. The &lt;code&gt;fdbcli&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; command &lt;code&gt;triggerddteaminfolog&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; triggers informative logs by invoking &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;release-7.3&#x2F;fdbserver&#x2F;DDTeamCollection.actor.cpp#L3425&quot;&gt;printSnapshotTeamsInfo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ServerTeamInfo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Priority&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;709&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Healthy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamSize&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;MemberIDs&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;5a69... 5fc1... 8718...&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;LoadBytes&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;1135157527&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;MinAvailableSpaceRatio&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0.94108&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;serverteamprioritychange-event&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#serverteamprioritychange-event&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: serverteamprioritychange-event&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;code&gt;ServerTeamPriorityChange&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Event&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event is logged when server team priorities change, often indicating server failures or rebalancing actions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ServerTeamPriorityChange&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Priority&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;950&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamID&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;e9b362decbafbd81&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;relocateshard-event&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#relocateshard-event&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: relocateshard-event&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;code&gt;RelocateShard&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Event&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event tracks shard movement between teams to maintain balance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RelocateShard&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Priority&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;120&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; PRIORITY_REBALANCE_UNDERUTILIZED_TEAM
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;RelocationID&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;3f1290654949771e&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the most useful field is the priority, indicating why it is relocated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;valleyfiller-and-mountainchopper-mechanisms&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#valleyfiller-and-mountainchopper-mechanisms&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: valleyfiller-and-mountainchopper-mechanisms&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&quot;ValleyFiller&quot; and &quot;MountainChopper&quot; Mechanisms&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To optimize shard placement, FoundationDB employs two balancing strategies:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ValleyFiller&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Fills underutilized servers (the &lt;strong&gt;valleys&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;) with data to balance the load.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MountainChopper&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Redistributes shards from overutilized servers (the &lt;strong&gt;mountains&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;) to spread the load evenly.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both logs will have a &lt;code&gt;SourceTeam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;DestTeam&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to use in other traces:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;BgDDValleyFiller&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;QueuedRelocations&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;SourceTeam&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamID 95819f0d3d7ea40d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;DestTeam&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamID 0817e6fe3135e6f6&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ShardBytes&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;398281250&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;json&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-json &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot; data-lang=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;BgDDMountainChopper&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;QueuedRelocations&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;SourceTeam&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamID 95819f0d3d7ea40d&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;DestTeam&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;TeamID e17dcecd86547e09&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;ShardBytes&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;308000000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">debugging</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Ensuring Safety in FoundationDB&#x27;s Rust Crate</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/providing-safety-fdb-rs/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/providing-safety-fdb-rs/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/providing-safety-fdb-rs/">&lt;p&gt;As we approach 5 million downloads of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;crates.io&#x2F;crates&#x2F;foundationdb&quot;&gt;FoundationDB Rust crate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (4,998,185 at the time of writing), I wanted to share some insights into how I ensure the safety of the crate. Being the primary maintainer of a database driver comes with responsibility, but I sleep well at night knowing that we have robust safety measures in place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;crate-overview&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#crate-overview&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: crate-overview&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Crate Overview&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rust crate, &lt;code&gt;foundationdb-rs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, provides bindings to interact with FoundationDB&#x27;s C API (&lt;code&gt;libfdb&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;). It has around 13k lines of code and is used by companies (like Clever Cloud) and projects (such as Apache OpenDAL, SurrealDB). Having experienced numerous outages and issues with drivers and distributed systems, I understand the importance of safety. To ensure the safety of the crate, we need to focus on three layers:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The underlying client, &lt;code&gt;libfdb&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The crate itself,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The code that uses the crate.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s dig into each of these areas.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;libfdb-safety&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#libfdb-safety&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: libfdb-safety&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;libfdb Safety&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the simplest part. &lt;code&gt;libfdb&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&#x27;s safety is guaranteed by FoundationDB&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;testing.html&quot;&gt;simulation framework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Therefore, we can consider it safe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;classic-testing-suite&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#classic-testing-suite&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: classic-testing-suite&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Classic testing suite&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we are using a C library, we need to use FFI (Foreign Function Interface) and unsafe code blocks. With around 130 unsafe blocks, we must be extra careful when calling C code, ensuring all preconditions are met. Naturally, we conduct extensive testing, but most importantly, we run tests in high-variety environments:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On multiple operating systems (Ubuntu, macOS)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On multiple FoundationDB versions (from FDB 6.1 to 7.3)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On multiple Rust compiler versions (Minimum Supported Rust Version or MSRV, stable, beta, nightly)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful tests are run on the nightly Rust compiler, as we can catch &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;issues&#x2F;90&quot;&gt;new behaviors in the Rust compiler early&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these testing practices provide significant coverage, the most powerful tool we utilize comes from FoundationDB’s maintainers: the &lt;code&gt;BindingTester&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bindingtester&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-bindingtester&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-bindingtester&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The BindingTester&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB is renowned for its &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;testing.html&quot;&gt;simulation and testing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; frameworks. Bindings are no exception. They developed the BindingTester, a cross-language validation suite ensuring that all bindings behave correctly and consistently across different languages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BindingTester uses &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;bindings&#x2F;bindingtester&#x2F;spec&#x2F;bindingApiTester.md&quot;&gt;a stack-based machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to queue operations for FoundationDB. A program then reads the stack and performs the operations. These operations are run twice: once in the target environment and once against a reference implementation. Any differences are reported by the BindingTester.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;.&#x2F;bindings&#x2F;bindingtester&#x2F;bindingtester.py --num-ops&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 1000&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --api-version&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 730&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --test-name&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; api&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --compare&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; python rust
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Creating&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test at API version 730
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Generating&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; api test at seed 3208032894 with 1000 op(s) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 1 concurrent tester(s)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Inserting Rust tests
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Inserting&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test into database...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Running&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tester &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;home&#x2F;runner&#x2F;work&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;target&#x2F;debug&#x2F;bindingtester test_spec 730&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;workspace&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;stack&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Inserting Python tests
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Inserting&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test into database...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Running&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tester &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;python &#x2F;home&#x2F;runner&#x2F;work&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;target&#x2F;foundationdb_build&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;bindings&#x2F;bindingtester&#x2F;..&#x2F;python&#x2F;tests&#x2F;tester.py test_spec 730&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;workspace&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;stack&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Comparing the results
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Comparing&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;workspace&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Comparing&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; results from &amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;tester_output&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;stack&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;#39;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Test&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; with seed 3208032894 and concurrency 1 had 0 incorrect result(s) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 0 error(s) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;at&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; API version 730
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Completed&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; api test with random seed 3208032894 and 1000 operations
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great advantage of this method is that the tests are seeded, meaning the operations are:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;randomly selected to cover all binding usages,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deterministic, so a failing seed can be replayed locally.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with code coverage, this gives us a good idea of what has been tested (though code coverage may vary).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We run the &lt;code&gt;BindingTester&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;every hour&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; on our GitHub actions, amounting to &lt;strong&gt;around 219 days of continuous testing each month&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (316,335 minutes of correctness last month according to Github).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-safety&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#user-safety&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: user-safety&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;User Safety&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;code&gt;libfdb&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;BindingTester&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, we can ensure that the library is quite safe. But what about the user&#x27;s code? How can we help users ensure their code can handle all of FoundationDB&#x27;s caveats, such as &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;automatic-txn-fdb-730&#x2F;#transactions-with-unknown-results&quot;&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;? We added a great feature: the ability to include Rust code &lt;strong&gt;within FDB&#x27;s simulation framework&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can implement an Rust workload with the following Trait:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;pub trait &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;RustWorkload {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;description&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) -&amp;gt; String;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;setup&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;static mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: SimDatabase, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;done&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Promise);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;start&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;static mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: SimDatabase, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;done&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Promise);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;check&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;static mut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: SimDatabase, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;done&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;: Promise);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;get_metrics&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) -&amp;gt; Vec&amp;lt;Metric&amp;gt;;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;fn &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;get_check_timeout&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;amp;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) -&amp;gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;f64&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which can be runned inside the simulation while injecting some faults:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;fdbserver -r&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; simulation&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; -f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &#x2F;root&#x2F;atomic.toml&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; -b&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; on&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt; --trace-format&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; json
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Choosing a random seed
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Random&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; seed is 394378360...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Then, everything is derived from the seed, including:
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# * cluster topology,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# * cluster configuration,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# * timing to inject faults,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# * operations to run
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# * ...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Datacenter&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 0: 3&#x2F;12 machines, 1&#x2F;1 coordinators
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Datacenter&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 1: 3&#x2F;12 machines, 0&#x2F;1 coordinators
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Datacenter&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 2: 3&#x2F;12 machines, 0&#x2F;1 coordinators
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Datacenter&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 3: 3&#x2F;12 machines, 0&#x2F;1 coordinators
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;# Starting the Atomic workload
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Run&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test:AtomicWorkload start
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;AtomicWorkload&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; complete
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;checking&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test (AtomicWorkload)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test clients passed; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test clients failed
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Run&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; test:AtomicWorkload Done.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tests passed; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tests failed.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Unseed:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 66324
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Elapsed:&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; 405.055622 simsec, 30.342000 real seconds
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a &lt;strong&gt;major keypoint&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for us to develop and operate &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;materia&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Materia, Clever Cloud&#x27;s serverless database offer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, as we can enjoy the same Simulation framework used by FDB&#x27;s core engineers for layer engineering 🤯&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-words&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#closing-words&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: closing-words&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Closing words&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any open-source project, there is always more to accomplish, but I am quite satisfied with the current level of safety provided by the crate. I would like to express my gratitude to the FoundationDB community for developing the BindingTester, and former contributors to the crate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also would like to encourage everyone to explore the simulation framework. Integrating Rust code within this framework has allowed us to harness the full potential of simulation without the need to build our own, and it has forever changed my perspective on testing and software engineering.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a strong likelihood that future blog posts will focus on simulation, so feel free to explore the &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;tags&#x2F;simulation&#x2F;&quot;&gt;simulation tags&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">rust</category>
          <category domain="tag">testing</category>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Redwood’s memory tuning in FoundationDB</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:37:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/redwood-memory-tuning/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/redwood-memory-tuning/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/redwood-memory-tuning/">&lt;p&gt;While FoundationDB allows you to obtain sub-milliseconds transactions’s latency without any knob-tuning, we had to bump a bit memory usage for Redwood under certain usage and workload. The following configuration has been tested on clusters from 7.1 to 7.3.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;btree-page-cache&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#btree-page-cache&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: btree-page-cache&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;BTree page cache&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discovered the issue when we saw a performance decrease on our cluster storing time-series data. Our cluster was reporting some high disk-business, causing outages:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;10.0.3.23:4501 ( 65% cpu; 61% machine; 0.010 Gbps; 93% disk IO; 7.5 GB &#x2F; 7.4 GB RAM  )
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;10.0.3.24:4501 ( 61% cpu; 61% machine; 0.010 Gbps; 87% disk IO; 9.7 GB &#x2F; 7.4 GB RAM  )
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;10.0.3.25:4501 ( 69% cpu; 61% machine; 0.010 Gbps; 93% disk IO; 5.4 GB &#x2F; 7.4 GB RAM  )
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was our first «we need to dig into this» moment with FDB. We couldn’t find the root-cause and we asked the community. Turns out we had a classic page-cache issue which was spotted by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;u&#x2F;markus.pilman&#x2F;summary&quot;&gt;Markus Pilman&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;u&#x2F;wmd&#x2F;summary&quot;&gt;William Dowling&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. While the trace files are pretty verbose, they are containing a lot of information like this one:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;PagerCacheHit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;39852&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;PagerCacheMiss&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;25903&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep, that’s a 40% cache-miss ratio over 5s 😱 This is why the disk was so busy, spending his time moving pages back and forth. We need to bump the memory, but how much? The general recommandation that worked for us is to target around 1-2% of the &lt;code&gt;kvstore_used_bytes&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; metrics. As we have around 1TiB of data per StorageServer, we can add the following config key:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;cache_memory = 10GiB
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which fixed our cache-miss issue 🎉&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;PagerCacheHit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;51968&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;PagerCacheMiss&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;432&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;byte-sample-memory-usage&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#byte-sample-memory-usage&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: byte-sample-memory-usage&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Byte Sample memory usage&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But our problems are still unresolved, as we are still seeing some OOM 😭 Because this cluster is storing time-series data, each StorageServers is holding around 1TiB of data. As we were holding more and more data, we saw more and more OOM errors on our &lt;code&gt;fdbmonitor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; logs. Something was growing linearly with our usage and needed tuning. This time, we had help from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;u&#x2F;SteavedHams&#x2F;summary&quot;&gt;Steve Atherton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which pointed us towards the direction of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;t&#x2F;foundationdb-7-1-24-the-memory-usage-after-clean-startup-of-fdbserver-process-is-too-high&#x2F;3863&#x2F;8?u=pierrez&quot;&gt;Byte Sample&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a data structure that storage servers have called the Byte Sample which stores a deterministic random sample of keys. This data is persisted on disk in the storage engine and is loaded immediately upon storage server startup. Unfortunately, its size is not tracked or reported, but grows linearly with KV size and I suspect yours is somewhere around 4GB-6GB based on the memory usage I’ve seen for smaller storage KV sizes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we need to add around 4GB more in the memory, but there is no config for that parameter. It needs to be embedded in the global &lt;code&gt;memory&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; parameter. Let’s compute the right value!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-global-memory-formula&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-global-memory-formula&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-global-memory-formula&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The global memory formula&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By testing things on our clusters, we ended up with this formula:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;# Default is 2
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;cache_memory = (1-2% of kvstore_used_bytes)GiB
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;# Default is 8
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;memory = (8 + cache_memory + 4-6GB per TB of kvstore_used_bytes)GiB
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which fixed all our memory issues with FoundationDB 🎉 And to be fair, this is the only things we needed to tune on our clusters, which is quite impressive 👀&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-thanks&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#special-thanks&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: special-thanks&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Special thanks&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Markus, William and Steve from the FoundationDB community for their help 🤝&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">performance</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">tuning</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>True idempotent transactions with FoundationDB 7.3</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:37:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/automatic-txn-fdb-730/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/automatic-txn-fdb-730/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/automatic-txn-fdb-730/">&lt;p&gt;I have been working around &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;foundationdb.org&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for several years now, and the new upcoming version is fixing one of the most evil and painful caveats you can deal with when writing layers: &lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transactions-with-unknown-results&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#transactions-with-unknown-results&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: transactions-with-unknown-results&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Transactions with unknown results&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start writing code with FDB, you may be under the assertions that given the database’s robustness, you will not experience some strange behavior under certain failure scenarios. Turns out, there is one scenario that is possible to reach, and quickly explained in the official &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;developer-guide.html#transactions-with-unknown-results&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with other client&#x2F;server databases, in some failure scenarios a client may be unable to determine whether a transaction succeeded. In these cases, commit() will raise a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;api-error-codes.html#developer-guide-error-codes&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; exception. The on_error() function treats this exception as retriable, so retry loops that don’t check for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;api-error-codes.html#developer-guide-error-codes&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; could execute the transaction twice. In these cases, you must consider the idempotency of the transaction.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While having idempotent retry loops is possible, sometimes it is not possible, for example when using atomic operations to keep track of statistics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this problem worth fixing? Seems a really edgy case 🤔&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It truly depends whether it is acceptable for your transaction to be committed twice. For most of the case, it is not, but sometimes developers are not aware of this behavior, leading to errors. This is one of the reasons why we worked and open-sourced a way to embed rust-code within FoundationDB’s simulation framework. Using the simulation crate, your layer can be tested like FDB, and I can assure you: you &lt;strong&gt;will see&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; those transactions in simulation 🙈.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This behavior has given headache to my colleagues, as we tried to bypass correctness and validation code in simulation when transactions state are unknown, and who could blame us? Validate the correctness of your code is hard when certains transactions (for example, one that could clean everything) are “maybe committed”. Fortunately, the community has released a workaround for this: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;release-7.3&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;sphinx&#x2F;source&#x2F;automatic-idempotency.rst&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;automatic idempotency&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;automatic-idempotency&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#automatic-idempotency&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: automatic-idempotency&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Automatic idempotency&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation is fairly explicit:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the automatic_idempotency transaction option to prevent commits from failing with &lt;code&gt;commit_unknown_result&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; at a small performance cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The option appeared in FoundationDB 7.3, and could solve our issue. I decided to give it a try and modify the foundationdb-simulation crate example. The example is trying to use a atomic increment under simulation. Before 7.1, during validation, we had to write &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;blob&#x2F;98136cbea1c9b8d40ea9a599438ce0fa8d0297c0&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&#x2F;examples&#x2F;atomic&#x2F;workload.rs#L99C1-L99C94&quot;&gt;some code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; We don&amp;#39;t know how much maybe_committed transactions has succeeded,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; so we are checking the possible range
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.success_count &amp;lt;= count
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;   &amp;amp;&amp;amp; count &amp;lt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.expected_count + &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.maybe_committed_count {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; ...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was adding 7.3 support in the crate, I decided to update the example and try the new option:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Enable idempotent txn
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; trx.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;set_option&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(TransactionOption::AutomaticIdempotency)?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the behavior is correct, I can simplify my consistency checks:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.success_count == count {
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;self&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.context.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;trace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        Severity::Info,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;Atomic count match&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;        details![],
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;     );
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; ...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been running hundreds of seeds on my machine and everything works great: no more maybe-committed transactions! Now that 7.3 support is merged in the rust bindings, we will be able to expands our testing thanks to our simulation farm. I&#x27;m also looking to see the performance impact of the feature, even if I&#x27;m pretty sure that it will outperform any layer-work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is truly a very useful feature and I hope this option will be turned on by default on the next major release. The initial PR can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;pull&#x2F;8398&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
          <category domain="tag">transactions</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Crafting row keys in FoundationDB</title>
          <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 00:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/crafting-keys-in-fdb/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/crafting-keys-in-fdb/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/crafting-keys-in-fdb/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;fdb-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#x27;m working &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Clikengo&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;issues&#x2F;27&quot;&gt;on my latest contribution around FoundationDB and Rust&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I had the chance to dig a bit into how FoundationDB&#x27;s bindings are offering helpers to generate keys. Their approach is interesting enough to deserve a blogpost 😎&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;row-key&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#row-key&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: row-key&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Row key?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are using a key&#x2F;value store, the design of the &lt;code&gt;row key&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is extremely important, as this will define how well:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your scans will be optimized,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your puts will be spread,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you will avoid &lt;code&gt;hot-spotting&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; a shard&#x2F;region.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need more information on &lt;code&gt;row keys&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, I recommend going through these links before moving on:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloud.google.com&#x2F;bigtable&#x2F;docs&#x2F;schema-design&quot;&gt;&quot;Designing your schema&quot; BigTable documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hbase.apache.org&#x2F;book.html#rowkey.design&quot;&gt;&quot;Rowkey Design&quot; HBase documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hand-crafting-row-keys&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#hand-crafting-row-keys&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: hand-crafting-row-keys&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Hand-crafting row keys&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, you will need to craft the &lt;code&gt;row key&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; &quot;by hand&quot;, like this for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;senx&#x2F;warp10-platform&#x2F;blob&#x2F;879734d7f63791b487f3e535cd79ac4c23e99377&#x2F;warp10&#x2F;src&#x2F;main&#x2F;java&#x2F;io&#x2F;warp10&#x2F;continuum&#x2F;store&#x2F;Store.java#L1215-L1222&quot;&gt;an HBase&#x27;s app&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;java&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-java &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Prefix + classId + labelsId + timestamp
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; 128 bits
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;byte[]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; rowkey = &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;new byte&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Constants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;HBASE_RAW_DATA_KEY_PREFIX&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.length + &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;];
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;System&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;arraycopy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Constants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;HBASE_RAW_DATA_KEY_PREFIX&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, rowkey, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Constants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;HBASE_RAW_DATA_KEY_PREFIX&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.length);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Copy classId&#x2F;labelsId
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;System&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;arraycopy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Longs&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;toByteArray&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(msg.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;getClassId&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, rowkey, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Constants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;HBASE_RAW_DATA_KEY_PREFIX&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.length, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;System&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;arraycopy&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Longs&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;toByteArray&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(msg.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;getLabelsId&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;()), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, rowkey, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ebcb8b;&quot;&gt;Constants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;HBASE_RAW_DATA_KEY_PREFIX&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.length + &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe you will wrap things in a function &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pingcap&#x2F;tidb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;ef57bdbbb04f60a8be744060a99207e08a37514a&#x2F;tablecodec&#x2F;tablecodec.go#L80-L86&quot;&gt;like this in Go&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;go&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-go &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-go&quot; data-lang=&quot;go&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; EncodeRowKey encodes the table id and record handle into a kv.Key
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;func &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8fa1b3;&quot;&gt;EncodeRowKey&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tableID &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;int64&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;encodedHandle &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;byte&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;kv&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;Key &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;make&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;([]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;byte&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;prefixLen&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;len&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;encodedHandle&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;))
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;appendTableRecordPrefix&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tableID&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;append&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;encodedHandle&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;...)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;return &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;buf
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time, you need to wrap the complexity of converting your objects to a row-key, by creating a buffer and write stuff in it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our Java example, there is an interesting comment:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;java&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-java &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; Prefix + classId + labelsId + timestamp
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are replacing some characters, we are not really far from:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;java&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-java &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot; data-lang=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; (Prefix, classId, labelsId, timestamp)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which looks like a &lt;code&gt;Tuple&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;(a collection of values of different types) and this is what FoundationDB is using as an abstraction to create keys 😍&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fdb-s-abstractions-and-helpers&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#fdb-s-abstractions-and-helpers&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: fdb-s-abstractions-and-helpers&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;FDB&#x27;s abstractions and helpers&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tuple&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tuple&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tuple&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Tuple&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of crafting bytes by hand, we are &lt;code&gt;packing&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; a Tuple:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; create a Tuple&amp;lt;String, i64&amp;gt; with (&amp;quot;tenant-42&amp;quot;, 1)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; tuple = (String::from(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant-42&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; and compute a row-key from the Tuple
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; row_key = foundationdb::tuple::pack::&amp;lt;(String, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;i64&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&amp;gt;(&amp;amp;tuple);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generated row-key will be readable from any bindings, as it&#x27;s construction is standardized. Let&#x27;s print it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; and print-it in hexa
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;println!(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;{:#04X?}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, row_key);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;txt&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-txt &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-txt&quot; data-lang=&quot;txt&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; can be verified with https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.utf8-chartable.de&#x2F;unicode-utf8-table.pl
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x02,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x65, &#x2F;&#x2F; e 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x61, &#x2F;&#x2F; a
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2D, &#x2F;&#x2F; -
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x31, &#x2F;&#x2F; 1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x15,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2A, &#x2F;&#x2F; 42
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, &lt;code&gt;pack&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; added some extra-characters. There are used to recognized the next type, a bit like when you are encoding&#x2F;decoding some wire protocols. You can find the relevant documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;design&#x2F;tuple.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having this kind of standard means that we can easily decompose&#x2F;&lt;code&gt;unpack&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; retrieve the user and the magic number In a Tuple (String, i64)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; from_row_key = foundationdb::tuple::unpack::&amp;lt;(String, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;i64&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&amp;gt;(&amp;amp;row_key)?;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;println!(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;user=&amp;#39;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;{}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;, magic_number=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;{}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, from_row_key.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, from_row_key.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; user=&amp;#39;tenant-42&amp;#39;, magic_number=42
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we saw &lt;code&gt;Tuples&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, let&#x27;s dig in the next abstraction: &lt;code&gt;subspaces&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;subspace&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#subspace&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: subspace&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Subspace&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are working with key-values store, we are often playing with what we call &lt;code&gt;keyspaces&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, by dedicating a portion of the key to an usage, like this for example:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;txt&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-txt &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-txt&quot; data-lang=&quot;txt&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;users&#x2F;tenant-1&#x2F;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;users&#x2F;tenant-2&#x2F;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;users&#x2F;tenant-3&#x2F;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;code&gt;&#x2F;users&#x2F;tenant-1&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can be view like a prefix where we will put all the relevant keys. Instead of passing a simple prefix, FoundationDB is offering a dedicated structure called a &lt;code&gt;Subspace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Subspace represents a well-defined region of keyspace in a FoundationDB database&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It provides a convenient way to use FoundationDB tuples to define namespaces for different categories of data. The namespace is specified by a prefix tuple which is prepended to all tuples packed by the subspace. When unpacking a key with the subspace, the prefix tuple will be removed from the result.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the &lt;code&gt;Subspace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is heavily relying on FoundationDB&#x27;s tuples, as we can &lt;code&gt;pack&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;unpack&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a best practice, API clients should use at least one subspace for application data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as we have now the tools to handle keyspaces easily, it is now futile to craft keys by hand 🙃 Let&#x27;s create a subspace!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;rust&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-rust &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-rust&quot; data-lang=&quot;rust&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; create a subspace from the Tuple (&amp;quot;tenant-1&amp;quot;, 42)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; subspace = Subspace::from((String::from(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant-1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;42&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;));
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; let&amp;#39;s print the range
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;println!(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;start: {:#04X?}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;\n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt; end: {:#04X?}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, subspace.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;().&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, subspace.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;range&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;().&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;);
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see observe this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;txt&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-txt &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-txt&quot; data-lang=&quot;txt&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; can be verified with https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.utf8-chartable.de&#x2F;unicode-utf8-table.pl
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;start: [
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x02,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x65, &#x2F;&#x2F; e 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x61, &#x2F;&#x2F; a
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2D, &#x2F;&#x2F; -
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x31, &#x2F;&#x2F; 1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x15,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2A, &#x2F;&#x2F; 42
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00, &#x2F;&#x2F; smallest possible byte
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;end: [
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x02,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x65, &#x2F;&#x2F; e 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x61, &#x2F;&#x2F; a
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x6E, &#x2F;&#x2F; n
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x74, &#x2F;&#x2F; t
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2D, &#x2F;&#x2F; -
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x31, &#x2F;&#x2F; 1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x15,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x2A, &#x2F;&#x2F; 42
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0x00,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    0xFF, &#x2F;&#x2F; biggest possible byte
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which make sens, if we take &lt;code&gt;(&quot;tenant-1&quot;, 42)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as a prefix, then the range for this subspace will be between &lt;code&gt;(&quot;tenant-1&quot;, 42, 0x00)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;(&quot;tenant-1&quot;, 42, 0xFF)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;directory&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#directory&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: directory&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Directory&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we know our way around &lt;code&gt;Tuples&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Subspaces&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, we can now talk about what I&#x27;m working on, which is the &lt;code&gt;Directory&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Let&#x27;s have a look at the relevant &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;developer-guide.html#directories&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB provides directories (available in each language binding) as a tool for managing related subspaces.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directories are a recommended approach for administering applications. Each application should create or open at least one directory to manage its subspaces.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, let&#x27;s see the API(in Go, as I&#x27;m working on the Rust API):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;go&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-go &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-go&quot; data-lang=&quot;go&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;subspace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;directory&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;CreateOrOpen&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;string&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;application&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;my-app&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant-42&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;}, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;nil&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;!= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;nil &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;log&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Fatal&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;fmt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Printf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;%+v&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;\n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;subspace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Bytes&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; [21 18]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that we have a shorter subspace! The &lt;code&gt;directory&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; allows you to generate some integer that will be bind to a path, like here &lt;code&gt;&quot;application&quot;, &quot;my-app&quot;, &quot;tenant&quot;, &quot;tenant-42&quot;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two advantages to this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shorter keys,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheap metadata operations like &lt;code&gt;List&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Move&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;go&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-go &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-go&quot; data-lang=&quot;go&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; list all tenant in &amp;quot;application&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;my-app&amp;quot;:
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tenants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;directory&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;List&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;string&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;application&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;my-app&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;})
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;!= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;nil &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;log&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Fatal&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;fmt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Printf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;%+v&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;\n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;tenants&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; [tenant-42]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; renaming &amp;#39;tenant-42&amp;#39; in &amp;#39;tenant-142&amp;#39;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; This will NOT move the data, only the metadata is modified
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;directorySubspace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;directory&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Move&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;string&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;application&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;my-app&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant-42&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;},  &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; old path
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;string&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;application&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;my-app&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a3be8c;&quot;&gt;tenant-142&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;}) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; new path
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#b48ead;&quot;&gt;if &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;!= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;nil &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;log&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Fatal&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;err&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;fmt&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Printf&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#d08770;&quot;&gt;%+v&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#96b5b4;&quot;&gt;\n&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;quot;, &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;directorySubspace&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;Bytes&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;())
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#65737e;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; still [21 18]
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The returned object is actually a &lt;code&gt;DirectorySubspace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which implements both &lt;code&gt;Directory&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Subspace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which means that you can use it to recreate many directories and subspaces at will 👌&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are wondering about how this integer is generated, I recommend going through this awesome blogpost on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;activesphere.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2018&#x2F;08&#x2F;05&#x2F;high-contention-allocator&quot;&gt;how high contention allocator works in FoundationDB.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Announcing Record-Store, a new (experimental) place for your data</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 10:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/announcing-record-store/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/announcing-record-store/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/announcing-record-store/">&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: I&#x27;m really happy to announce my latest open-source project called Record-Store 🚀 Please check it out on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrez.github.io&#x2F;record-store&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrez.github.io&#x2F;record-store&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;What?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Record-Store&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;layer-concept.html&quot;&gt;layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; running on top of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;foundationdb.org&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It provides abstractions to create, load and deletes customer-defined data called &lt;code&gt;records&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which are hold into a &lt;code&gt;RecordSpace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. We would like to have this kind of flow for developers:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opening RecordSpace, for example &lt;code&gt;prod&#x2F;users&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a protobuf definition which will be used as schema&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upsert schema&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push records&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Query records&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;delete records&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need another &lt;code&gt;KeySpace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to store another type of data, or maybe a &lt;code&gt;KeySpace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; dedicated to production env? Juste create it and you are good to go!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#features&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: features&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Features&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is currently an experiment, but it already has some strong features:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-tenant&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; A &lt;code&gt;tenant&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; can create as many &lt;code&gt;RecordSpace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as we want, and we can have many &lt;code&gt;tenants&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard API&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; We are exposing the record-store with standard technologies:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;grpc.io&quot;&gt;gRPC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;very experimental&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;graphql.org&quot;&gt;GraphQL&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalable&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; We are based on the same tech behind &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.foundationdb.org&#x2F;files&#x2F;record-layer-paper.pdf&quot;&gt;CloudKit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; called the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;fdb-record-layer&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transactional&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; We are running on top of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.foundationdb.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. FoundationDB gives you the power of ACID transactions in a distributed database.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encrypted&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Data are encrypted by default.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-model&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; For each &lt;code&gt;RecordSpace&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, you can define a &lt;code&gt;schema&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which is in-fact only a &lt;code&gt;Protobuf&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; definition. You need to store some &lt;code&gt;users&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, or a more complicated structure? If you can represent it as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developers.google.com&#x2F;protocol-buffers&quot;&gt;Protobuf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, you are good to go!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Index-defined queries&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Your queries&#x27;s capabilities are defined by the indexes you put on your schema.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secured&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; We are using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;CleverCloud&#x2F;biscuit&quot;&gt;Biscuit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a mix of &lt;code&gt;JWT&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Macaroons&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to ensure auth{entication, orization}.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#why&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: why&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Why?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been playing a lot with my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-etcd&quot;&gt;ETCD-Layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that is using the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;fdb-record-layer&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Record-Layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Thanks to it, I was able to bootstrap my ETCD-layer very quickly, but I was not using a tenth of the capacities of this library. So I decided to go deeper. &lt;strong&gt;What would a gRPC abstraction of the Record-Layer look like?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of this project itself is a tribute to the Record Layer as we are exposing the layer within a gRPC interface.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;try-it-out&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#try-it-out&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: try-it-out&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Try it out&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record-Store is open sourced under Apache License V2 in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;record-store&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;record-store&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the documentation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrez.github.io&#x2F;record-store&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrez.github.io&#x2F;record-store&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
          <category domain="tag">opensource</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Notes about FoundationDB</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 10:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;fdb-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;tags&#x2F;notes&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Notes About&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a blogpost serie  you will find a lot of &lt;strong&gt;links, videos, quotes, podcasts to click on&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; about a specific topic. Today we will discover FoundationDB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview-of-foundationdb&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#overview-of-foundationdb&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: overview-of-foundationdb&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Overview of FoundationDB&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;official documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB is a distributed database designed to handle large volumes of structured data across clusters of commodity servers. It organizes data as an ordered key-value store and employs ACID transactions for all operations. It is especially well-suited for read&#x2F;write workloads but also has excellent performance for write-intensive workloads.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has strong key points:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-model data store&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily scalable and fault tolerant&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Industry-leading performance&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open source.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a database dialect, it provides:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;jepsen.io&#x2F;consistency&#x2F;models&#x2F;strict-serializable&quot;&gt;strict serializability&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;(operations appear to have occurred in some order),&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloud.google.com&#x2F;spanner&#x2F;docs&#x2F;true-time-external-consistency&quot;&gt;external consistency&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;(For any two transactions, T1 and T2, if T2 starts to commit after T1 finishes committing, then the timestamp for T2 is greater than the timestamp for T1).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-story&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-story&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-story&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The story&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB started as a company in 2009, and then &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;techcrunch.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;03&#x2F;24&#x2F;apple-acquires-durable-database-company-foundationdb&#x2F;&quot;&gt;has been acquired in 2015 by Apple&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=9259986&quot;&gt;was a bad public publicity for the database as the download were removed.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 19, 2018, Apple &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.foundationdb.org&#x2F;blog&#x2F;foundationdb-is-open-source&#x2F;&quot;&gt;open sourced the software, releasing it under the Apache 2.0 license&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tooling-before-coding&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#tooling-before-coding&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: tooling-before-coding&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Tooling before coding&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;flow&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#flow&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: flow&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Flow&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;engineering.html&quot;&gt;Engineering page&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB began with ambitious goals for both high performance per node and scalability. We knew that to achieve these goals we would face serious engineering challenges that would require tool breakthroughs. We’d need efficient asynchronous communicating processes like in Erlang or the Async in .NET, but we’d also need the raw speed, I&#x2F;O efficiency, and control of C++. To meet these challenges, we developed several new tools, the most important of which is &lt;strong&gt;Flow&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, a new programming language that brings actor-based concurrency to C++11.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow is more of a &lt;strong&gt;stateful distributed system framework&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; than an asynchronous library. It takes a number of highly opinionated stances on how the overall distributed system should be written, and isn’t trying to be a widely reusable building block.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow adds about 10 keywords to C++11 and is technically a trans-compiler: the Flow compiler reads Flow code and compiles it down to raw C++11, which is then compiled to a native binary with a traditional toolchain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flow was developed before FDB, as stated in this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=5319163&quot;&gt;2013&#x27;s post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB founder here. Flow sounds crazy. What hubris to think that you need a new programming language for your project? Three years later: Best decision we ever made.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew this was going to be a long project so we invested heavily in tools at the beginning. The first two weeks of FoundationDB were building this new programming language to give us the speed of C++ with high level tools for actor-model concurrency. But, the real magic is how Flow enables us to use our real code to do deterministic simulations of a cluster in a single thread. We have a white paper upcoming on this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;ve had quite a bit of interest in Flow over the years and I&#x27;ve given several talks on it at meetups&#x2F;conferences. We&#x27;ve always thought about open-sourcing it... It&#x27;s not as elegant as some other actor-model languages like Scala or Erlang (see: C++) but it&#x27;s nice and fast at run-time and really helps productivity vs. writing callbacks, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Fun fact: We&#x27;ve only ever found two bugs in Flow. After the first, we decided that we never wanted a bug again in our programming language. So, we built a program in Python that generates random Flow code and independently-executes it to validate Flow&#x27;s behavior. This fuzz tester found one more bug, and we&#x27;ve never found another.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very good overview of Flow is available &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;flow.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and some details &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;t&#x2F;why-was-flow-developed&#x2F;1711&#x2F;3&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;simulation-driven-development&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#simulation-driven-development&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: simulation-driven-development&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Simulation-Driven development&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Flow’s most important job is enabling &lt;strong&gt;Simulation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted FoundationDB to survive failures of machines, networks, disks, clocks, racks, data centers, file systems, etc., so we created a simulation framework closely tied to Flow. By replacing physical interfaces with shims, replacing the main epoll-based run loop with a time-based simulation, and running multiple logical processes as concurrent Flow Actors, Simulation is able to conduct a deterministic simulation of an entire FoundationDB cluster within a single-thread! Even better, we are able to execute this simulation in a deterministic way, enabling us to reproduce problems and add instrumentation ex post facto. This incredible capability enabled us to build FoundationDB exclusively in simulation for the first 18 months and ensure exceptional fault tolerance long before it sent its first real network packet. For a database with as strong a contract as the FoundationDB, testing is crucial, and over the years we have run the equivalent of a trillion CPU-hours of simulated stress testing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good overview of the simulation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;testing.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. You can also have a look at this awesome talk!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;4fFDFbi3toc&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulation has been made possible by combining:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single-threaded pseudo-concurrency,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simulated implementation of all external communication,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;determinism.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s an example of a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;tests&#x2F;slow&#x2F;SwizzledCycleTest.txt&quot;&gt;testfile&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;testTitle=SwizzledCycleTest
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testName=Cycle
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    transactionsPerSecond=5000.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testDuration=30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    expectedRate=0.01
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testName=RandomClogging
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testDuration=30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    swizzle = 1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testName=Attrition
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    machinesToKill=10
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    machinesToLeave=3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    reboot=true
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testDuration=30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testName=Attrition
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    machinesToKill=10
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    machinesToLeave=3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    reboot=true
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testDuration=30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    testName=ChangeConfig
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    maxDelayBeforeChange=30.0
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;    coordinators=auto
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test is splitted into two parts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, for example doing transaction pointing to another with thousands of transactions per sec and there should be only 0.01% of success.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will be done to try to prevent the test to succeed&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. In this example it will &lt;strong&gt;at the same time&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do random clogging. Which means that &lt;strong&gt;network connections will be stopped&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (preventing actors to send and receive packets). Swizzle flag means that a subset of network connections will be stopped and bring back in reverse order, 😳&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;will &lt;strong&gt;poweroff&#x2F;reboot machines&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (attritions) pseudo-randomly while keeping a minimal of three machines, 🤯&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;change configuration&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, which means a coordination changes through multi-paxos for the whole cluster. 😱&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that all these failures will appears &lt;strong&gt;at the same time!&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Do you think that your current &lt;strong&gt;datastore has gone through the same test on a daily basis?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;etcd-io&#x2F;etcd&#x2F;pull&#x2F;11308&quot;&gt;I think not&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications written using the FoundationDB simulator have hierarchy: &lt;code&gt;DataCenter -&amp;gt; Machine -&amp;gt; Process -&amp;gt; Interface&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Each of these can be killed&#x2F;freezed&#x2F;nuked&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Even faulty admin commands fired by some DevOps are tested!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;known-limitations&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#known-limitations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: known-limitations&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Known limitations&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limitations are well described in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;known-limitations.html&quot;&gt;official documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recap&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#recap&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: recap&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Recap&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An awesome recap is available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;softwareengineeringdaily.com&#x2F;2019&#x2F;07&#x2F;01&#x2F;foundationdb-with-ryan-worl&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Software Engineering Daily podcast&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB is tested in a very rigorous way using what&#x27;s called &lt;strong&gt;a deterministic simulation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The reason they needed a new programming language to do this, is that to get a deterministic simulation, you have to make something that is deterministic. It&#x27;s kind of obvious, but it&#x27;s hard to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if your process interacts with the network, or disks, or clocks, it&#x27;s not deterministic. If you have multiple threads, not deterministic. So, they needed a way to write a concurrent program that could talk with networks and disks and that type of thing. They needed a way to write a concurrent program that does all of those things that you would think are non-deterministic in a deterministic way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, all FoundationDB processes, and FoundationDB, it&#x27;s basically all written in Flow except a very small amount of it from the SQLite B-tree. The reason why that was useful is that when you use Flow, you get all of these higher level abstraction that let what you do what feels to you like asynchronous stuff, but under the hood, it&#x27;s all implemented using callbacks in C++, which you can make deterministic by running it in a single thread. So, there&#x27;s a scheduler that just calls these callbacks one after another and it&#x27;s very crazy looking C++ code, like you wouldn&#x27;t want to read it, but it&#x27;s because of Flow they were able to implement that deterministic simulation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-architecture&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-architecture&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-architecture&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Architecture&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.github.io&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;administration.html#fdbmonitor-and-fdbserver&quot;&gt;fdbmonitor and fdbserver&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core FoundationDB server process is &lt;code&gt;fdbserver&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Each &lt;code&gt;fdbserver&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; process uses up to one full CPU core, so a production FoundationDB cluster will usually run N such processes on an N-core system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make configuring, starting, stopping, and restarting fdbserver processes easy, FoundationDB also comes with a singleton daemon process, &lt;code&gt;fdbmonitor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, which is started automatically on boot. &lt;code&gt;fdbmonitor&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; reads the &lt;code&gt;foundationdb.conf&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file and starts the configured set of fdbserver processes. It is also responsible for starting backup-agent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole architecture is designed to automatically:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;load-balanced data and traffic,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;self-healing.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;microservices&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#microservices&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: microservices&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Microservices&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical FDB cluster is composed of different actors which are describe &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;sphinx&#x2F;source&#x2F;kv-architecture.rst&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important role in FDB is the &lt;code&gt;Coordinator&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, it uses &lt;code&gt;Paxos&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to manage membership on a quorum to do writes. The &lt;code&gt;Coordinator&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is mostly only used to elect some peers and during recovery. You can view it as a Zookeeper-like stack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Coordinator starts by electing a &lt;code&gt;Cluster Controller&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. It provides administratives informations about the cluster(I have 4 storage processes). Every process needs to register to the &lt;code&gt;Cluster Controller&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and then it will assign roles to them. It is the one that will heart-beat all the processes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a &lt;code&gt;Master&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is elected. The &lt;code&gt;Master&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; process is reponsible for the &lt;code&gt;data distribution&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; algorithms. Fun fact, the mapping between keys and storage servers is stored within FDB, which is you can actually move data by running transactions like any other application. He is also the one providing &lt;code&gt;read versions&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;version number&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; internally. He is also acting as the &lt;code&gt;RateKeeper&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The Proxies&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are responsible for providing read versions, committing transactions, and tracking the storage servers responsible for each range of keys.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The Transaction Resolvers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are responsible determining conflicts between transactions. A transaction conflicts if it reads a key that has been written between the transaction’s read version and commit version. The resolver does this by holding the last 5 seconds of committed writes in memory, and comparing a new transaction’s reads against this set of commits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;architecture.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-and-write-path&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#read-and-write-path&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: read-and-write-path&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Read and Write Path&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;EMwhsGsxfPU&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;read-path&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#read-path&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: read-path&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Read Path&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retrieve a consistend read version for the transaction&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do reads from a consistent MVCC snapshot at that read version on the storage node&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;write-path&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#write-path&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: write-path&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Write Path&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;client is sending a bundle to the &lt;code&gt;proxy&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; containing:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read version for the transaction&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every readen key&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every mutation that you want to do&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The proxy will assign a &lt;code&gt;Commit version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to a batch of transactions. &lt;code&gt;Commit version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is generated by the &lt;code&gt;Master&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proxy is sending to the resolver. This will check if the data that you want to mutate has been changed between your &lt;code&gt;read Version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and your &lt;code&gt;Commit version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. They are sharded by key-range.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transaction is made durable within the &lt;code&gt;Transaction Logs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; by &lt;code&gt;fsync&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;ing the data. Before the data is even written to disk it is forwarded to the &lt;code&gt;storage servers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; responsible for that mutation. Internally, &lt;code&gt;Transactions Logs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are creating &lt;strong&gt;a stream per &lt;code&gt;Storage Server&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Once the &lt;code&gt;storage servers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; have made the mutation durable, they pop it from the log. This generally happens roughly 6 seconds after the mutation was originally committed to the log.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Storage servers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are lazily updating data on disk from the &lt;code&gt;Transaction logs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. They are keeping new write in-memory.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Transaction Logs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is responding OK to the Proxy and then the proxy is replying OK to the client.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more diagrams about transactions &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;t&#x2F;technical-overview-of-the-database&#x2F;135&#x2F;3&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recovery&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#recovery&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: recovery&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Recovery&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recovery processes are detailled at around 25min.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During failure of a process (Except storage servers), the systems will try to create a new &lt;code&gt;generation&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, so new &lt;code&gt;Master&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;proxies&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;resolvers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;transactions logs&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. New master will get a read version from transactions logs, and commit with &lt;code&gt;Paxos&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; the fact that starting from &lt;code&gt;Read version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, the new generation is the one in charge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Storage servers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are replicating data on failures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-5-second-transaction-limit&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-5-second-transaction-limit&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-5-second-transaction-limit&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The 5-second transaction limit&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB currently does not support transactions running for over five seconds. More details around 16min but the &lt;code&gt;tl;dr&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storage servers are caching latest read in-memory,&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolvers are caching the last 5 seconds transactions.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ratekeeper&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#ratekeeper&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: ratekeeper&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Ratekeeper&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details around 31min but the &lt;code&gt;tl;dr&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is that when system is saturated, retrieving the &lt;code&gt;Read version&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is slowed down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;storage&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#storage&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: storage&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Storage&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of information are available in this talk:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;nlus1Z7TVTI&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;memory&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; is optimized for small databases. Data is stored in memory and logged to disk. In this storage engine, all data must be resident in memory at all times, and all reads are satisfied from memory.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;SSD&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Storage Engine is based on SQLite B-Tree&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Redwood&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; will be a new storage engine based on Versioned B+Tree&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;developer-experience&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#developer-experience&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: developer-experience&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Developer experience&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FoundationDB’s keys are ordered, making &lt;code&gt;tuples&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; a particularly useful tool for data modeling. FoundationDB provides a &lt;strong&gt;tuple layer&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (available in each language binding) that encodes tuples into keys. This layer lets you store data using a tuple like &lt;code&gt;(state, county)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as a key. Later, you can perform reads using a prefix like &lt;code&gt;(state,)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. The layer works by preserving the natural ordering of the tuples.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is wrapped into a transaction in FDB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a nice overview by reading the README of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;richardartoul&#x2F;tsdb-layer&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;README.md&quot;&gt;tsdb-layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, an experiment combining Time Series and FoundationDB: Millions of writes&#x2F;s and 10x compression in under 2,000 lines of Go.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fdb-one-more-things-layers&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#fdb-one-more-things-layers&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: fdb-one-more-things-layers&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;FDB One more things: Layers&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;concept-of-layers&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#concept-of-layers&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: concept-of-layers&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Concept of layers&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;HLE8chgw6LI&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FDB is resolving many distributed problems, but you still need things like &lt;strong&gt;security, multi-tenancy, query optimizations, schema, indexing&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;extract-layer-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layers are designed to develop features &lt;strong&gt;above FDB.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The record-layer provided by Apple is a good starting point to build things above it, as it provides &lt;strong&gt;structured schema, indexes, and (async) query planner.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;extract-layer-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The record-layer provided by Apple is a good starting point to build things above it, as it provides &lt;strong&gt;structured schema, indexes, and (async) query planner.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;extract-layer-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;apple-s-record-layer&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#apple-s-record-layer&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: apple-s-record-layer&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Apple&#x27;s Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is located &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;pdf&#x2F;1901.04452.pdf&quot;&gt;FoundationDB Record Layer:A Multi-Tenant Structured Datastore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;SvoUHHM9IKU&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record Layer was designed to solve CloudKit problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;record-extract-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record allow multi-tenancy with schema above FDB&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;record-extract-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;record-extract-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record Layers is providing stateless compute&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;record-extract-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And streaming queries!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;record-extract-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kubernetes-operators&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#kubernetes-operators&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: kubernetes-operators&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Kubernetes Operators&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-the-operator&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#overview-of-the-operator&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: overview-of-the-operator&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Overview of the operator&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;div &gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe
        src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;A3U8M8pt3Ks&quot;
        webkitallowfullscreen
        mozallowfullscreen
        allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;operator-extract-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;operator-extract-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrade is done by &lt;strong&gt;bumping all processes at once&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; 😱&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;operator-extract-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;notes-about-foundationdb&#x2F;operator-extract-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;fdb image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;combining-chaos-mesh-and-the-operator&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#combining-chaos-mesh-and-the-operator&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: combining-chaos-mesh-and-the-operator&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Combining chaos-mesh and the operator&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played a bit with the operator by combining:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;FoundationDB&#x2F;fdb-kubernetes-operator&quot;&gt;FoundationDB&#x2F;fdb-kubernetes-operator&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pingcap&#x2F;go-ycsb&quot;&gt;pingcap&#x2F;go-ycsb&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pingcap&#x2F;chaos-mesh&quot;&gt;pingcap&#x2F;chaos-mesh&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-prometheus-exporter&#x2F;&quot;&gt;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-prometheus-exporter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment is available &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;fdb-k8s-chaos&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;roadmap&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#roadmap&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: roadmap&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Roadmap&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;foundationdb&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;FoundationDB-Release-7.0-Planning&quot;&gt;FoundationDB Release 7.0 Planning&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">distributed</category>
          <category domain="tag">foundationdb</category>
          <category domain="tag">storage</category>
          <category domain="tag">database</category>
          <category domain="tag">notes</category>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
