<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks on Pierre Zemb</title>
    <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks on Pierre Zemb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34;&gt;Some Rights Reserved&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 12:22:36 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bookkeeper 101</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/bookkeeper-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 12:22:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/bookkeeper-101/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Apache Bookkeeper is the main datastore used by Apache Pulsar. This Top-Level Apache project is defined as « A scalable, fault-tolerant, and low-latency storage service optimized for real-time workloads ». BookKeeper is suitable for a wide variety of use cases, from WAL to storage. In this talk, we will dive into Bookkeeper’s concepts, the public API, deployments and how it is used within Pulsar.
Occurences  HUG France: Special Apache Pulsar Meetup  Ressources  slides  Photos and tweets Si vous cherchez à organiser les MeetUP, nos bureaux à Paris, Nantes, Rennes, Lyon, Bordeaux, Brest, Wroclaw, Madrid, Milan, London, Montreal, Dallas, Reston sont dispo gratos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring OVH: 300k servers, 27 DCs and one metrics platform</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/one-monitoring-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 17:24:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/one-monitoring-platform/</guid>
      <description>Abstract What to do when you must monitor the whole infrastructure of the biggest European hosting and cloud provider? How to choose a tool when the most used ones fail to scale to your needs? How to build an Metrics platform to unify, conciliate and replace years of fragmented legacy partial solutions?
In this talk we will relate our experience building and maintaining OVH Metrics, the platform used to monitor all OVH infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operate JVM at Scale</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/handling-jvm-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 22:18:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/handling-jvm-scale/</guid>
      <description>Abstract OVH has 27 data centers, more than 300 000 servers and 1.3 million customers. We operate one of the world’s largest cloud infrastructures on a daily basis, running millions of applications. Those softwares manage millions of transactions every second. To monitor such an architecture, OVH has chosen to build a unified monitoring platform: OVH Metrics Data Platform. Such a platform uses complex distributed systems to operate, based mainly on open source tools running on the JVM (Apache Kafka, Apache HBase, Warp 10, …).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling alerts at OVH-Scale with Apache Flink</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/ovh-alerts-flink/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 22:22:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/ovh-alerts-flink/</guid>
      <description>Abstract OVH relies heavily on metrics to effectively monitor its entire infrastructure. Offering a low-level vision and business, these allow teams to better operate the daily operation of our services. After managing more than 300 TB of telemetry, we started working on an alerting solution over this huge datalake. For that, we decided to use Apache Flink to manage all these large scale alerts. Today, this project manages the alerting of flagship OVH products such as Public Cloud Instances and Kubernetes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What we learned as DevOps @OVH</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/devops-ovh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 22:22:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/devops-ovh/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Have you been wondered what is like to be working at the largest European Cloud Provider as a DevOps ? Despite both working on differents teams and products, we have a lot in common, such as good practices, organizations, technologies and even our good mood ! Time to lift the curtain! We will share with you perspectives from two DevOps: one working on OVH managed Kubernetes product and one working on Metrics, OVH distributed monitoring platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rediscover the known data universe with NASA dataset</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/nasa-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 19:11:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/nasa-datasets/</guid>
      <description>Abstract For many years humanity has been exploring the skies, dreaming of interstellar voyages and new planetary colonies. And you, do you want to go 3h with us to discover the universe?
It turns out that NASA has a great public dataset, especially one that is used to search for exoplanets, that is, planets outside our solar system.
During this Hands-on, we will guide you through the different stages of rediscovering exoplanets using Warp10, an open-source time series processing platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One day into the Time Series&#39;s world</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/one-day-timeseries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 22:22:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/one-day-timeseries/</guid>
      <description>Abstract This is a one-day course I am giving at my former engineering school ISEN Brest.
Schedule  Introduction to Time Series Time Series in real life Code instrumentation Lab: searching for exoplanets  Ressources  slides  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metrics Experience beyond protocols</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/metrics-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 15:38:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/talks/metrics-experience/</guid>
      <description>Occurences  Paris Open Source Summit, 2017  Ressources The slides are available here.
Photos and Tweets Let&amp;#39;s discover @OvhMetrics experience with @PierreZ at #OSSPARIS17 pic.twitter.com/Xz1tRTNcFW
&amp;mdash; Collignon Rémi (@miton1810) December 7, 2017  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>