<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on website</title>
    <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 22:07:11 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing with TTL in HBase</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ttl-hbase/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 22:07:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ttl-hbase/</guid>
      <description>Among all features provided by HBase, there is one that is pretty handy to deal with your data&amp;rsquo;s lifecyle: the fact that every cell version can have Time to Live or TTL. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the feature!
Time To Live (TTL) Let&amp;rsquo;s read the doc first!
 ColumnFamilies can set a TTL length in seconds, and HBase will automatically delete rows once the expiration time is reached.
 HBase Book: Time To Live (TTL)</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling OVH&#39;s alerts with Apache Flink</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ovh-alerts-flink/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 15:37:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ovh-alerts-flink/</guid>
      <description>This is a repost from OVH&amp;rsquo;s official blogpost.. Thanks Horacio Gonzalez for the awesome drawings!
Handling OVH&amp;rsquo;s alerts with Apache Flink OVH relies extensively on metrics to effectively monitor its entire stack. Whether they are low-level or business centric, they allow teams to gain insight into how our services are operating on a daily basis. The need to store millions of datapoints per second has produced the need to create a dedicated team to build a operate a product to handle that load: **Metrics Data Platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What are ACID transactions?</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/acid-transactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 15:37:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/acid-transactions/</guid>
      <description>Transaction? &amp;quot;Programming should be about transforming data&amp;quot;  &amp;mdash; Programming Elixir 1.3 by Dave Thomas
As developers, we are interacting oftenly with data, whenever handling it from an API or a messaging consumer. To store it, we started to create softwares called relational database management system or RDBMS. Thanks to them, we, as developers, can develop applications pretty easily, without the need to implement our own storage solution. Interacting with mySQL or PostgreSQL have now become a commodity.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hbase Data Model</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/hbase-data-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 20:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/hbase-data-model/</guid>
      <description>HBase?  Apache HBase™ is a type of &amp;ldquo;NoSQL&amp;rdquo; database. &amp;ldquo;NoSQL&amp;rdquo; is a general term meaning that the database isn’t an RDBMS which supports SQL as its primary access language. Technically speaking, HBase is really more a &amp;ldquo;Data Store&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;Data Base&amp;rdquo; because it lacks many of the features you find in an RDBMS, such as typed columns, secondary indexes, triggers, and advanced query languages, etc.
 &amp;ndash; Hbase architecture overview</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing HelloExoWorld: The quest to discover exoplanets with Warp10 and Tensorflow</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/introducing-helloexoworld-the-quest-to-discover-exoplanets-with-warp10-and-tensorflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 10:23:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/introducing-helloexoworld-the-quest-to-discover-exoplanets-with-warp10-and-tensorflow/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
Artist’s impression of the super-Earth exoplanet LHS 1140b By ESO/spaceengine.org — CC BY 4.0
My passion for programming was kind of late, I typed my first line of code at my engineering school. It then became a passion, something I’m willing to do at work, on my free-time, at night or the week-end.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Engage maximum warp speed in time series analysis with WarpScript</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/engage-maximum-warp-speed-in-time-series-analysis-with-warpscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 20:43:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/engage-maximum-warp-speed-in-time-series-analysis-with-warpscript/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
We, at Metrics Data Platform, are working everyday with Warp10 Platform, an open source Time Series database. You may not know it because it’s not as famous as Prometheus or InfluxDB but Warp10 is the most powerful and generic solution to store and analyze sensor data. It’s the core of Metrics, and many internal teams from OVH are using Metrics Data Platform to monitor their infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Event-driven architecture 101</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/eventdriven-architecture-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 17:19:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/eventdriven-architecture-101/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
Do your own cover on http://dev.to/rly
I’m still a student, so my point of view could be far from reality, be gentle ;)
tl;dr: Queue messaging are cool. Use them at the core of your architecture.I’m currently playing a lot around Kafka and Flink at work. I also discovered Vert.x at my local JUG.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Let’s talk about containers</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/lets-talk-about-containers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 18:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/lets-talk-about-containers/</guid>
      <description>update 2019: this is a repost on my own blog. original article can be read on medium.
English is not my first language, so the whole story may have some mistakes… corrections and fixes will be greatly appreciated. I’m also still a student, so my point of view could be far from “production ready”, be gentle ;-)
In the last two years, there’s been a technology that became really hype.</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>