<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Pierre Zemb&#x27;s Blog - personal</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr</link>
      <description>Pierre Zemb personal blog</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/personal/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>2025: A Year in Review</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/2025-year-in-review/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/2025-year-in-review/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/2025-year-in-review/">&lt;p&gt;2025 was the year I stopped managing and started shipping software again. After nearly two years of context-switching between fires and people issues, I returned to the keyboard. As the year closes, it feels like the right time to look back. It was about &lt;strong&gt;going deeper&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: into code, into writing, and into understanding why simulation testing is a superpower.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-in-engineering&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#back-in-engineering&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: back-in-engineering&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Back in Engineering&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-transition&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-transition&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-transition&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Transition&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, I &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;back-engineering&#x2F;&quot;&gt;went back to engineering&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; after nearly two years in management. It felt like coming home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I will be honest: the transition was harder than I expected. There was real imposter syndrome. Had I lost my edge? Was I still the technical person I used to be? The hardest part was not the code itself but giving myself &lt;strong&gt;permission to focus&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Having another engineering manager handle the team and another SRE team handling the fires while I dove into low-level work was the perfect setup. I am also &lt;strong&gt;grateful&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to the whole team for making that transition possible. But after three years of context-switching between fires and people issues, sitting down to write code without interruption felt almost wrong. It took months to fully allow myself to focus without afterthoughts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-the-toolbox-behind-materia-the-long-way-around&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#building-the-toolbox-behind-materia-the-long-way-around&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: building-the-toolbox-behind-materia-the-long-way-around&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Building the Toolbox Behind Materia, the Long Way Around&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helping put &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;company&#x2F;2025&#x2F;06&#x2F;27&#x2F;why-we-finally-built-our-own-managed-kubernetes-etcd&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clever Cloud&#x27;s etcd shim&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; into production was meaningful because of the long arc behind it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At OVHcloud, I got paged too often when etcd hit its performance ceiling. We were adding hundreds of customers per etcd cluster, each with their own Kubernetes control plane. I &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=IrJyrGQ_R9c&quot;&gt;talked about this at KubeCon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Spawning three etcd nodes per customer is not a valid approach at scale, whether in the cloud or on-premise. You need to mutualize, but you cannot scale etcd horizontally because the whole keyspace must fit on every member and the recommended storage limit is &lt;strong&gt;8GB&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. When you outgrow one cluster, you boot another, split your keys, and now you operate two, three, or many clusters. We had to balance customers manually across clusters. After &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;hbase-custom-data-balancing&#x2F;&quot;&gt;contributing a custom balancer to HBase&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to solve exactly this problem, doing it by hand for etcd felt like going backward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I discovered Apple&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrez.github.io&#x2F;fdb-book&#x2F;the-record-layer&#x2F;what-is-record-layer.html&quot;&gt;FDB Record Layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It was an eye-opener: here was a way to &lt;strong&gt;virtualize database-like systems&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; on top of FoundationDB, building any storage abstraction you want on a rock-solid distributed foundation. During France&#x27;s first lockdown, I &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.foundationdb.org&#x2F;t&#x2F;a-foundationdb-layer-for-apiserver-as-an-alternative-to-etcd&#x2F;2697&quot;&gt;prototyped an etcd layer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; using the Record Layer. The prototype worked, but more importantly, the Record Layer showed me what was important: &lt;strong&gt;a reusable toolbox to encapsulate FoundationDB knowledge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved to Clever Cloud to build exactly that: serverless systems based on FoundationDB. We started building the toolbox in Rust, piece by piece, driven by what our layers actually needed. Our first layer was &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;product&#x2F;materia-kv&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Materia KV&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, exposing the Redis protocol. That forced us to build the foundational primitives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One highlight was building the query engine for Materia. I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;datafusion-contrib&#x2F;datafusion-index-provider&quot;&gt;datafusion-index-provider&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a library that extends Apache DataFusion with index-based query acceleration. I had a lot of fun digging into how a query plan might look when fetching indexes: a two-phase model where you first scan indexes to identify matching row IDs, then fetch complete records. The interesting part was combining &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;OR&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; operations. AND predicates build a left-deep tree of joins to intersect row IDs across indexes. OR predicates use unions with deduplication to merge results without fetching the same record twice. The first time DataFusion, FoundationDB, and our indexes all connected and a SELECT query returned real data, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;thank-you-datafusion&#x2F;&quot;&gt;I remembered why I write software&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came etcd, which required &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; more work: watches, leases, revision tracking. I &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;diving-into-kubernetes-watch-cache&#x2F;&quot;&gt;debugged the watch cache&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; along the way. We are not alone in this approach: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;aws.amazon.com&#x2F;blogs&#x2F;containers&#x2F;under-the-hood-amazon-eks-ultra-scale-clusters&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AWS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cloud.google.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;products&#x2F;containers-kubernetes&#x2F;gke-65k-nodes-and-counting?hl=en&quot;&gt;GKE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; also run custom storage layers for Kubernetes at scale. No more splitting clusters, no more manual data balancing, no more operational nightmares. FoundationDB handles the hard distributed systems parts. Years of frustration with etcd turned into an etcd-compatible API backing Kubernetes control planes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-simulation-year&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-simulation-year&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-simulation-year&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Simulation Year&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-awakening&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#the-awakening&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: the-awakening&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;The Awakening&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bugbash.antithesis.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;BugBash 2025&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in early April.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference in Washington D.C., organized by Antithesis, brought together people like Kyle Kingsbury, Ankush Desai, and Mitchell Hashimoto to discuss software reliability. The highlight was meeting some of the original FoundationDB creators. Hearing their war stories and seeing how deeply simulation shaped FDB&#x27;s legendary reliability reignited something in me. I had been using FDB&#x27;s simulation for years, but I had never fully internalized that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;simulation-driven-development&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this could be how I write all software&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BugBash reminded me of my painful on-call years at OVHcloud. Before etcd, I operated a massive HBase cluster: 255 machines, 2 million writes per second, 6 million reads. HBase was weak to network issues, and every incident triggered region split inconsistencies. We ran hbck in brutal ways just to keep things running. HBase led me to FDB, a system &lt;strong&gt;built to handle network chaos&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and that robustness comes from simulation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-understanding-to-building&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#from-understanding-to-building&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: from-understanding-to-building&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;From Understanding to Building&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025 was about turning that understanding into something real. At work, we added simulation workloads to critical software running on top of Materia. I &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.google.com&#x2F;presentation&#x2F;d&#x2F;1xm4yNGnV2Oi8Lk3ZHEvg4aDMNEFieSmW06CkItCigSc&#x2F;edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;spoke at Devoxx France&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; about embracing simulation-driven development. But I wanted to go deeper: to understand how FoundationDB created its robustness. So I &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;diving-into-foundationdb-simulation&#x2F;&quot;&gt;dug into the implementation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, then started backporting it to Rust.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That became &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;PierreZ&#x2F;moonpool&quot;&gt;moonpool&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I split moonpool into four crates, each a foundational block for distributed systems. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.rs&#x2F;moonpool-core&#x2F;latest&#x2F;moonpool_core&#x2F;&quot;&gt;moonpool-core&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; defines provider traits for time, networking, task spawning, and randomness. Same code runs in production and simulation. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.rs&#x2F;moonpool-sim&#x2F;latest&#x2F;moonpool_sim&#x2F;&quot;&gt;moonpool-sim&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is the simulation engine: virtual time, event queues, and fault injection. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.rs&#x2F;moonpool-transport&#x2F;latest&#x2F;moonpool_transport&#x2F;&quot;&gt;moonpool-transport&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; provides FDB-style RPC: connection management, checksummed wire formats, automatic reconnection. Claude accelerated this work significantly. I used it to translate C++ patterns into Rust. At some point, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;testing-prevention-vs-discovery&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Claude started fixing bugs on its own&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2025, I had basic knowledge of deterministic simulation. By the end, I had built a framework. In 2026, I will start a &lt;strong&gt;blogpost series&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; explaining moonpool&#x27;s internals. Maybe it becomes something others can use. Maybe it stays a hobby project. Either way, I am convinced: &lt;strong&gt;simulation is the future&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sharing&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#sharing&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: sharing&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Sharing&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set a goal to write one or two posts per month, and I published 22. You can trace my monthly focus just by looking at what I published. The results surprised me: traffic multiplied by 2.5x according to Plausible. This was also the first year where people actually reached out to say &lt;strong&gt;thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for sharing. I always assumed no one was reading.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top posts by visitors: &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;nixos-good-bad-ugly&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NixOS: The Good, The Bad, and The Ugly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;tokio-hidden-gems&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Unlocking Tokio&#x27;s Hidden Gems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;distsys-resources&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Distributed Systems Resources&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;simulation-driven-development&#x2F;&quot;&gt;What if we embraced simulation-driven development?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Strangely enough, my most shared post was not about distributed systems or FoundationDB but about NixOS. I think people appreciated the honest take: the good, the bad, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; the ugly. The Tokio post being #2 was also unexpected. Sometimes the posts you almost do not publish are the ones that resonate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love making presentations. In 2025, I gave two talks at Devoxx France: one about &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.google.com&#x2F;presentation&#x2F;d&#x2F;1xm4yNGnV2Oi8Lk3ZHEvg4aDMNEFieSmW06CkItCigSc&#x2F;edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;simulation-driven development&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and another about &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.google.com&#x2F;presentation&#x2F;d&#x2F;1UbJ7drA_6hX7kLN2nV8IxOsAt1k8WOnfGrEfRlbIa7k&#x2F;edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;prototyping distributed systems with Maelstrom&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I also presented &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.google.com&#x2F;presentation&#x2F;d&#x2F;13pCaWXNkITj5Sh4dKofILbxPg_Wb2BBedbbi2Mv4PoE&#x2F;edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;my fdb-rs journey&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;finistdevs.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FinistDevs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which I help organize in Brest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;crates.io&#x2F;crates&#x2F;foundationdb&quot;&gt;FoundationDB Rust crate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; keeps growing: 11 million downloads, used in production by real companies. But I was not a great maintainer this year. Development followed Clever Cloud&#x27;s requirements. People asked for documentation about simulation testing and a roadmap, and I did not deliver. That is not a complaint about open source, just honesty. Being a solo maintainer without foundation backing means priorities get driven by the day job. Last week I finally wrote a roadmap and flushed my brain into GitHub issues so contributors can pick up work. I hope to do better in 2026.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-llms-changed-my-work&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#how-llms-changed-my-work&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: how-llms-changed-my-work&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;How LLMs Changed My Work&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot write about 2025 without talking about LLMs. I spent a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of time learning how to use them in my work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, I had a weekly habit: two hours dedicated to reading codebases I depend on, understanding the internals of libraries, frameworks, and databases. Then I stopped. Life got busy, management took over, and diving into unfamiliar code took too long to justify. With LLMs, I picked the habit back up. What used to take hours now takes minutes. I can explore a codebase conversationally, asking questions, jumping to relevant sections, building mental models faster than ever. I learn more now than I did before.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They handle peripheral code well: glue code, boilerplate, scaffolding. Geoffrey Litt calls this &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.geoffreylitt.com&#x2F;2025&#x2F;10&#x2F;24&#x2F;code-like-a-surgeon&quot;&gt;coding like a surgeon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&quot;: delegate the prep work, focus on what matters. Moonpool is a good example. Claude translated C++ Flow patterns into Rust and generated test scaffolding. But knowing &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to translate required years of operating distributed systems: why FDB uses interface swapping, why buggify has two-phase activation, why virtual time compresses hours into seconds. As João Alves wrote, when &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;world.hey.com&#x2F;joaoqalves&#x2F;when-software-becomes-fast-food-23147c9b&quot;&gt;software becomes fast food&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&quot;, expertise becomes the scarce resource.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I did not expect is that working with LLMs forces me to flesh out invariants and hidden rules somewhere explicit. You need to write things down for the LLM to understand, and that documentation ends up being useful for humans too. &lt;strong&gt;Context is everything&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: given the right context, LLMs generate the right code. So I spent a lot of time (and tokens) generating project recaps and summaries to feed them. When working with libraries, I make local git clones so the LLM can browse the actual source code instead of relying on potentially outdated training data. I have been using Claude extensively, and I found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;github&#x2F;spec-kit&quot;&gt;spec-kit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; helpful for framing my prompts. It is a toolkit for &quot;spec-driven development&quot; that helps you focus on product scenarios instead of what Simon Willison calls &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;simonwillison.net&#x2F;2025&#x2F;Oct&#x2F;7&#x2F;vibe-engineering&#x2F;&quot;&gt;vibe coding&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&quot;. But &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;specs-are-back&#x2F;&quot;&gt;we are still missing the tools&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to make this workflow seamless.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some posts became unexpectedly useful as LLM context. My &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;practical-guide-to-application-metrics&#x2F;&quot;&gt;practical guide to application metrics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and my &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;writing-rust-fdb-workloads-that-find-bugs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;guidelines for FDB workloads&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; now live in project contexts. When I ask Claude to add instrumentation or write a simulation workload, it already knows my patterns.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-ahead&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#looking-ahead&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: looking-ahead&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025 reminded me why I love this work: building systems, learning in public, watching years of investment pay off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2026, the habits stay: writing one or two posts per month, reading codebases with LLM assistance, speaking at conferences. I want to push moonpool toward something others can actually use. We have ambitious plans for Materia at Clever Cloud, and some of them should lead me to contribute to FoundationDB directly. I will keep helping organize &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;finistdevs.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;FinistDevs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in Brest. And I will definitely be back at BugBash 2026.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme is the same as 2025: go deeper, share what I learn, build things that last. &lt;strong&gt;What did your 2025 look like?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out to share your own 2025 reflections. You can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bsky.app&#x2F;profile&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pierrezemb.fr&quot;&gt;website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">personal</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Back in engineering!</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:37:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/back-engineering/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/back-engineering/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/back-engineering/">&lt;p&gt;Time flies—it’s already 2025! Looking back, 2024 was an incredibly fast-paced year for me professionally as an Engineering Manager. This year, I’ve decided to take a new direction and return to a more engineering-focused role.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved in a management position early 2023. It was a time where my company was growing fast (from 20-ish to 60-ish), and we needed coordination to ship things out in parallel, but also to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;company&#x2F;2023&#x2F;12&#x2F;21&#x2F;our-journey-to-a-better-clever-cloud&#x2F;&quot;&gt;migrate customers (and ourselves!) to new datacenters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. With my on-call experience, I helped our CTO, Steven, bootstrap two data-oriented teams and later led the Materia team, shaping its technology.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time, we successfully launched &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clever-cloud.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;features&#x2F;2024&#x2F;06&#x2F;11&#x2F;materia-kv-our-easy-to-use-serverless-key-value-database-is-available-to-all&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Materia KV in its Alpha version&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and built strong internal trust in FoundationDB. Our largest cluster effortlessly handles hundreds of thousands of writes per second, and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;foundationdb-rs&#x2F;tree&#x2F;main&#x2F;foundationdb-simulation&quot;&gt;the ability to simulate Rust code within FDB’s simulation framework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has significantly boosted our developers&#x27; confidence.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management is a rewarding challenge, like unlocking a new skill tree to walk through. Resources like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.oreilly.com&#x2F;library&#x2F;view&#x2F;the-managers-path&#x2F;9781491973882&#x2F;&quot;&gt;The Manager&#x27;s Path&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.engmanagement.dev&quot;&gt;Engineering Management for the Rest of Us&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; can give you a head-start and should be read by anyone. Blogs like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charity.wtf&#x2F;tag&#x2F;management&#x2F;page&#x2F;2&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Charity Majors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are also useful to read, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charity.wtf&#x2F;2017&#x2F;05&#x2F;11&#x2F;the-engineer-manager-pendulum&#x2F;&quot;&gt;The Engineer&#x2F;Manager Pendulum&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and its &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;charity.wtf&#x2F;2019&#x2F;01&#x2F;04&#x2F;engineering-management-the-pendulum-or-the-ladder&#x2F;&quot;&gt;follow-up&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After nearly two years, I feel it&#x27;s the right time to return to core engineering. I just miss it.  From the start, my manager and I had an understanding that I could transition back whenever I wanted to—and that time is now. I&#x27;ve found an excellent manager to lead the team, giving me the space to focus on the technical side of Materia. I also should have more time to work around open-source, and I&#x27;m looking forward to it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">personal</category>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>10 years of programming and counting 🚀</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
          <author>Pierre Zemb</author>
          <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ten-years-programming/</link>
          <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ten-years-programming/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/ten-years-programming/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just realized that I’ve spent the last decade programming 🤯 While 2020 feels like a strange year, I thought it would be nice to write down a retrospective of the last 10 years 🗓&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-to-program-man-computer&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#learning-to-program-man-computer&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: learning-to-program-man-computer&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Learning to program 👨🏻‍💻&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote my first &lt;em&gt;Hello, world&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; program somewhere around September 2010, when I started my engineering school to do some electronics, but that C language got me. I spent 6 months struggling to understand pointers and memory. I remember spending nights trying to find a memory leak with valgrind. Of course there were multiples mistakes, but it felt good to dig that far.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also discovered Linux around that time, and spent many nights playing with Linux commands. I started my journey to Linux with Centos and then Ubuntu 11.04. I think this started the loop I’m (still!) stuck in:
&lt;code&gt;for {tryNewDistro()}&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;
I’m pretty sure that if I wanted to go away from distributed systems, I would try to land a job around operating systems. So many things to learn 🤩&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning C, we started to learn web-based technologies like HTML&#x2F;CSS&#x2F;JS&#x2F;PHP. I remember struggling to generate a calendar with PHP 🐘 I learned about APIs the week after the project 😅 I remember digging into cookies, and network calls from popular websites to see how they were using it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;java-and-hadoop-elephant&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#java-and-hadoop-elephant&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: java-and-hadoop-elephant&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Java and Hadoop 🐘&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the chance to land a part-time internship during the third year (out of five) of my engineering school. I joined the Systems team @ Arkea, a french bank.
I remember spending a lot of time with my coworkers, learning things from them, from Hadoop to mainframes and Linux. It was my first time grasping the work around “system programming”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first task was around writing an installer for a java app on windows, but my tutor tried to push me further. He saw my interest around some specific layers of their perimeter, such as Hadoop and Kafka. He gave to me a chance to work directly on those. A small API that was could load old monitoring data stored in HDFS and expose them back into the “real-time” visualization tool. I also used Kafka and even deployed a small HBase cluster for testing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#x27;t thank my tutor enough for giving me this chance, and for allowing me to discover what will become my focus: distributed systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;let-s-meet-other-people-wave&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#let-s-meet-other-people-wave&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: let-s-meet-other-people-wave&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Let’s meet other people 👋&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, I discovered tech meetups and conferences. At that time, Google I&#x2F;O was a major event with people jumping from a plane and streaming it through Google Glass. I found out there was a group of people watching the live together. And this is how I discovered my local GDG&#x2F;JUG 🥳 I learned so many things by watching local talks, even if it was difficult to grasp everything at first. I remember taking 📝 about what I didn’t understand, to learn about it later.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also met amazing persons, that are now friends and&#x2F;or mentors. I remember feeling humble to be able to learn from them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also discovered more global tech conferences. I asked as a birthday 🎁 to go to Devoxx France and DotScale, in 2014. It was awesome 😎&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By dint of watching talks, I wanted to give some. I started small, giving talks at my engineering school, then moved to the JUG itself. I learned &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; by making a lot of mistakes, but I’m pretty happy how things turned out, as I’m now speaking at tech conferences as part of my current work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;ten-years-programming&#x2F;first-talk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;etcd image&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started to be involved in events and organizations such as:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The JUG&#x2F;GDG&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A coworking place&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startup Weekend&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Devoxx4kids&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DevFest du bout du monde&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-big-data-floppy-disk&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#learning-big-data-floppy-disk&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: learning-big-data-floppy-disk&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Learning big data 💾&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my graduation and a(nother) part-time internship at OVH, I started working on something called Metrics Data Platform. It is the platform massively used internally to store, query and alert on timeseries data. We avoid the Borgmon approach (deploying Prometheus’s like database for every team), instead we created a unique platform to ingest all OVHcloud’s datapoints using a big-data approach. Here’s the key point of Metrics:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;multi-tenant&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: as we said before, a single metrics cluster is handling all telemetry, from servers to applications and smart data centers from OVHcloud.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;scalable&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: today we are receiving around 1.8 million datapoints per second&#x2F;s 🙈 for about 450 million timeseries 🙉. During European daytime, we are reading around 4.5 millions datapoints per seconds thank to Grafana’s auto-refresh mode 🙊&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;multi-protocol support&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: we didn&#x27;t want to reflect our infrastructure choice to our users, so we wrote some proxies that can translate known protocols to our query language, so users can query and push data using OpenTSDB, Prometheus, InfluxDB and so on.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;based on open source&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; we are using Warp10 as the core of our infrastructure with Kafka and HBase. Alerting was built with Apache flink. We open sourced many software, from agent to our proxies. We also gave many talks about what we learnt.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the chance to built Metrics from the ground. I started working on the management layer and proxies. Then I wanted to learn operations, so I learned it by deploying Hadoop clusters 🤯 it took me a while to be able to start doing on-calls. I cannot count how many nights I was up, trying to fix some buggy softwares, or yelling at HBase for an inconsistent &lt;code&gt;hbck&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, or trying to find a way to handle a side effect of a loosing multiple racks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work was highly technical, and I loved it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We optimized a lot of things, from HBase to our Go’s based proxies. &lt;code&gt;optimize HBase&#x27;s data balancer&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;fix issues with Go’s gc&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;  was almost a normal task to do&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We saw Metrics’s growth, from hundred to millions of datapoints 😎 we saw systems breaking at scale, causing us to rewrite software or change architecture. Production became the final test.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every software we developed had a &lt;code&gt;keep it simple, yet scalable&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; policy, and doing on-calls was a good way to ensure software quality. We all learned it the hard way I guess 🤣&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were only 4 to 6 to handle ~800 servers, 3 Hadoop clusters, and thousands of lines of Java&#x2F;Go&#x2F;Rust&#x2F;Ansible codes.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, things were not always magical, and i struggled more time than I can count. I learned that personal struggle is more difficult than technical, as you can always drill-down your tech problems by reading the code. The team was amazing 🚀, and we were helping each other a lot 🤝&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;searching-for-planets-telescope-ringed-planet&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#searching-for-planets-telescope-ringed-planet&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: searching-for-planets-telescope-ringed-planet&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Searching for planets 🔭 🪐&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started working on Metrics, we did a lot of internal on boarding. At his core, metrics is usine Warp10, which is coming with his own language to analyze timeseries. This provides heavy query-capabilities, but as it is stack-based, getting started was difficult. I needed a project to dive into timeseries analysis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love astronomy 🔭, but there’s too much ☁️ (not the servers) in my city. I decided to look for astronomical timeseries. Turns out there is a lot, but one use case triggered my interest: exoplanet’s search. Almost everything from NASA is Opendata, so we decided to create &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;helloexo.world&#x2F;&quot;&gt;HelloExoWorld&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We imported the &lt;strong&gt;25TB dataset into a Warp10 instance&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and start writing some WarpScript to search for transits. We wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;helloexoworld.github.io&#x2F;hew-hands-on&#x2F;&quot;&gt;hands-on about it&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. We also did several labs in french conferences like Devoxx and many others.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;io-timeout-construction&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#io-timeout-construction&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: io-timeout-construction&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;IO timeout 🚧&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2018, OVHcloud started Managed Kubernetes, a free K8S control-plane. With this product we saw more developers coming to OVHcloud. We started thinking about how we could help them. Running stateful systems is &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, so maybe we could offer them some databases or queues in a As-a-Service fashion. We started to design such products from our Metrics experience. We started the IO Vision to offer &lt;code&gt;popular Storage APIs in front of a scalable storage&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. Does it sound familiar? 😇 I had a lot of fun working on that vision as a Technical Leader.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with queuing with ioStream. We wanted something that was:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-tenant&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-protocol&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geo-replicated natively&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less operation burden at scale than Kafka&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We built ioStream around Apache Pulsar, and opened the beta around September 2019. As the same time we were working on Kafka’s support as a proxy in Rust. Writing such a software capable of translating Kafka’s TCP frames to Pulsar with a state-machine was a &lt;strong&gt;fun and challenging work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Rust is really a nice language to write such software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we worked with Apache Pulsar’s PMC to introduce a Kafka protocol handler on Pulsar brokers. I had the chance to work closely to two PMCs, it was an amazing experience for me 🚀 You can read about our collaboration &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.ovh.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;announcing-kafka-on-pulsar-bring-native-kafka-protocol-support-to-apache-pulsar&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately as stated by the official communication, the project has been shut down:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;However, the limited success of the beta service and other strategic focuses,
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;have resulted in us taking the very difficult decision to close it.
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot of things, both technically and on the product-side, especially considering the fact that it was shutdown.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#today&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: today&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;Today&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After ioStream’s shutdown, most of the team moved to create a new LBaaS. I helped them wrote an operator to schedule HAProxy’s containers on a Kubernetes cluster. It was a nice introduction to operators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I decided to join the Managed Kubernetes ☸️ team. This is my current team now, where I’m having a lot of fun working around ETCD.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope the next 10 years will be as fun as the last 10 years 😇&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for reading my post! Feel free to react to this article, I am also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;PierreZ&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; if needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
          <category domain="tag">personal</category>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
