<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>notesabout on Pierre Zemb</title>
    <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/notesabout/</link>
    <description>Recent content in notesabout on Pierre Zemb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&#34;&gt;Some Rights Reserved&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:24:27 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pierrezemb.fr/tags/notesabout/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes about ETCD</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-etcd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-etcd/</guid>
      <description>Notes About is a blogpost serie you will find a lot of links, videos, quotes, podcasts to click on about a specific topic. Today we will discover ETCD.
Overview of ETCD As stated in the official documentation:
 etcd is a strongly consistent, distributed key-value store that provides a reliable way to store data that needs to be accessed by a distributed system or cluster of machines. It gracefully handles leader elections during network partitions and can tolerate machine failure, even in the leader node.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes about Raft&#39;s paper</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-raft/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 07:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-raft/</guid>
      <description>Notes About is a blogpost serie you will find a lot of links, videos, quotes, podcasts to click on about a specific topic. Today we will discover Raft&amp;rsquo;s paper called &amp;lsquo;In Search of an Understandable Consensus Algorithm&amp;rsquo;.
 As I&amp;rsquo;m digging into ETCD, I needed to refresh my memory about Raft. I started by reading the paper located here and I&amp;rsquo;m also playing with the amazing Raft labs made by PingCAP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes about FoundationDB</title>
      <link>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 10:24:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pierrezemb.fr/posts/notes-about-foundationdb/</guid>
      <description>Notes About is a blogpost serie you will find a lot of links, videos, quotes, podcasts to click on about a specific topic. Today we will discover FoundationDB.
 Overview of FoundationDB As stated in the official documentation:
 FoundationDB is a distributed database designed to handle large volumes of structured data across clusters of commodity servers. It organizes data as an ordered key-value store and employs ACID transactions for all operations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
